
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>Clock Synchronization</title>
 <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>April 25, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.01</revnumber>
	<date>July 25, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Added sections for server and cluster</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.02</revnumber>
	<date>December 31, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Relative to RHEL 3.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.03</revnumber>
	<date>May 6, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Modified for firewall.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.04</revnumber>
	<date>June 24, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Modified treatment of cluster.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.05</revnumber>
	<date>December 3, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Added section on firewall configuration for webserver and
	removed section for cluster.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  <abstract>
    <para>
	It is important that the system clocks in the Linux 
	workstations of the RFPK Software Team be closely 
	synchronized to the clock in the server which hosts the CVS
	repository, or to the time standard to which that server is 
	synchronized, because the CVS application, as well as the
	backup process which runs on the same server, depend for their
	proper operation on the comparison of timestamps of files 
	residing on different.machines. This tutorial
	explains how to configure your workstation so that it
	stays synchronized within a fraction of a second with that
	server.
      </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Network Time Protocol</title>
    <para>
      The Network Time Protocol (NTP) allows computers connected
      to the Internet to keep their clocks synchronized.  Certain
      host computers equipped with accurate clocks make the NTP
      service available to other, less well endowed, hosts.  
      A machine with an accurate clock which is offering an NTP
      service is known as a <emphasis>level one</emphasis> NTP
      server.  Other machines, which may not be equipped with
      accurate clocks but which nevertheless have accurate time
      due to the fact that they are synchronized to one or more
      <emphasis>level one</emphasis> NTP servers, can offer an
      NTP service over the Internet as <emphasis>level two</emphasis>
      NTP servers, and so on.
    </para>
    <para>
      The host
      <systemitem moreinfo="none" class="systemname">
	bigben.cac.washington.edu
      </systemitem>
      is a <emphasis>level one</emphasis> NTP server equipped
      with a clock that gets its time from GPS satellites. 
      The RFPK CVS server
      is synchronized to 
      <systemitem moreinfo="none" class="systemname">bigben</systemitem>
      and several other <emphasis>level one</emphasis> NTP servers.
      This document describes the way to configure your 
      RedHat Linux 8.0 workstation to synchronize to 
      to one or the other of these servers.
    </para>
    <para>
      If your machine is on the LAN behind the SPK firewall, it can be 
      synchronized to the the CVS server, which is located on the LAN.
      If it is not on the LAN, it can be synchronized to 
      <systemitem moreinfo="none" class="systemname">
	bigben.cac.washington.edu
      </systemitem>
      or to some other external time server.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Defining Timeserver</title>
    <para>
      The following instructions will be easier to follow if we define
      a system alias for the 
      time server we are going to use.  This will also allow us to move
      machines from one network to another, only having to change the
      alias definition in a single file rather than references in a number
      of files.
    </para>
    <para>
      The changes will be made to the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file.
      There are the following cases:
      <orderedlist numeration="lowerroman">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Your machine is outside the firewall.  
	    Add the following line to <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>:
	    <screen>
140.142.16.34    bigben.cac.washington.edu   timeserver
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Your machine is behind the firewall and
	    there is already an entry for the CVS server (IP address
	    192.168.1.2) in your 
	    <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file.  In this case, simply add
	    <emphasis>timeserver</emphasis> to the end of that line.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Your machine is behind the firewall, but 
	    there is no entry for the CVS server.
	    Add the following line to 
	    <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>
	    <screen>
192.168.1.2 timeserver
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The machine is one of the computational (not frontend) nodes
	    in the cluster topology that contains a frontend.  The entry
	    in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> should look like this
	    <screen>
192.168.3.1    timeserver frontend
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring RFPK Software Development Clients</title>
    <para>
      This section covers the configuration of RFPK software development
      workstations and the cspk server.
      We must edit several configuration files. To do this, 
      you will need root privilege.
      <screen format="linespecific">
su -
cd /etc
      </screen>
      Edit <filename>ntp.conf</filename>
      with your favorite editor, setting the default behavior to 
      <emphasis>nomodify</emphasis> rather than 
      <emphasis>ignore</emphasis>.
      <screen format="linespecific">
restrict default ignore

	<emphasis>should be changed to</emphasis>

restrict default nomodify
      </screen>
      Next specify that 
      <systemitem moreinfo="none" class="systemname">timesever</systemitem>
      is a trusted time server by making this change:
      <screen format="linespecific">
	after

# restrict mytrustedtimeserverip mask 255.255.255.255 nomodify notap noquery
# server mytrustedtimeserverip

	insert the following pair of lines

restrict timeserver nomodify notrap noquery
server timeserver
      </screen>
      Save the file, after you have made your changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, we need to recreate the 
      <filename moreinfo="none">/etc/ntp/step-tickers</filename> file,
      which is a list of time servers queried by your system when it boots.
    </para>
    <para>
      <screen format="linespecific">
cd /etc/ntp
echo timeserver > step-tickers
echo time.nist.gov >> step-tickers
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Daemon Setup</title>
    <para>
      We need to start the ntp daemon, if it is not already running, and
      make sure that it is started automatically whenever the system reboots.
      As <systemitem moreinfo="none" class="username">root</systemitem>,
      input the following commands:
      <screen format="linespecific">
/etc/rc.d/init.d/ntpd restart
/sbin/chkconfig --level 2345 ntpd on
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      You should now check that your ntp daemon is working.
      Wait a few minutes after restarting ntpd, then issue this command:
      <screen format="linespecific">
/usr/sbin/ntpq -p
      </screen>
      You should see output that looks something like this:
      <screen format="linespecific">
     remote           refid      st t when poll reach   delay   offset  jitter
==============================================================================
 LOCAL(0)        LOCAL(0)        10 l   63   64  377    0.000    0.000   0.008
*whitechuck.rfpk bigben.cac.wash  2 u  192  256  377    0.684    0.075   0.024
      </screen>
      If delay, offset, and jitter are not small numbers, the clock has not
      synchronized, which may indicate that there is an error your configuration.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Extra Configuration for Webserver</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Webserver</emphasis> is on the orange LAN. The rest of the
      RFPK workstations and servers are either on the green LAN or on the
      public internet. The firewall greatly restricts network traffic between
      the green and orange LANs. The NTP setup for <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>
      is the same as for the rest of the clients with the exception
      that additional configuration must be done to the firewall.
      It is necessary to use the firewall administration interface to 
      create a pinhole between the IP address of <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>
      and the IP address of <emphasis>timeserver</emphasis> on port 123 for
      the TCP protocol, and another one on the same port for the UDP protocol.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title id="timeserver">Configuring the RFPK Timeserver</title>
    <para>
      The RFPK time server
      needs to be set up somewhat differently from the 
      workstations.
    </para>
    <para>
      Just as for workstations,
      the default should be edited to read
      <screen>
restrict default nomodify
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      The list of trusted servers, should read as follows:
      <screen>
restrict bigben.cac.washington.edu nomodify notrap noquery
restrict time.nist.gov nomodify notrap noquery
restrict tick.uh.edu nomodify notrap noquery
restrict tick.usno.navy.mil nomodify notrap noquery

server bigben.cac.washington.edu
server time.nist.gov
server tick.uh.edu
server tick.usno.navy.mil
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Unlike the workstation case, the server must be open to 
      clients.  Just following the commented CLIENT NETWORK
      section, add the following
      <screen>
restrict 192.168.0.0 mask 255.255.0.0 notrust nomodify notrap
      </screen>
      which enables service requests coming from any of the
      IP addresses behind the firewall in the 
      lab at AERL 241.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Additional lines, similar to the one above, can be added
      to accommodate RFPK machines with IP addresses that fall
      into other address ranges.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  afw RFPK whitechuck CVS NTP GPS bigben su cd ci nomodify ntp
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  mytrustedtimeserverip notap noquery notrap internet rcsdiff
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  conf chkconfig ntpd ntpq refid rfpk
 -->
