<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>Bugzilla Installation and Configuration</title>
 <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>June 8, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  <abstract>
      <para>
	Bugzilla is a powerful defect tracking system, used by RFPK as an important
	element in the operation of the SPK service, accessible via the world-wide-web
	at the url <emphasis>spk.rfpk.washington.edu</emphasis>
	Bugzilla is free software, distributed under an open source license.  It 
	is written in the perl language and requires a relational database management
	system (RDBMS) and a web server.  The recommended RDBMS is the open source
	MySQL, already incorporated in SPK.  The recommended web server is Apache
	httpd,
	which is not currently used by SPK.  This document includes instructions 
	for the configuration of MySQL and httpd to support Bugzilla.  It also 
	covers the installation of an additional package, called bugzilla-submit,
	which enables the SPK compiler and runtime daemons to automatically 
	report failures that they detect.
      </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Installation Overview</title>
    <para>
      The software components of the defect tracking system are installed on
      several different servers.  Just as it is possible to install all of SPK
      with the exception of the MDA on a single server, it is possible to 
      install the bugzilla system on a single server.  At RFPK, however, SPK
      is distributed across a number of servers and so, consequently, is 
      bugzilla.
    </para>
    <para>
      The components of the defect tracking system are distributed as follows:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Bugzilla and the Apache httpd  web server software must be installed together. 
	    For operational reasons, it makes sense to use the same machine that
	    hosts the tomcat web server software used by SPK.  This machine is
	    located on the orange network at 192.168.2.2 and will be referred to
	    as <emphasis>webserver</emphasis> in the remainder of this document.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Apache httpd is a already installed on <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>, as 
	    part of the installation of the Redhat Linux operating system.  All
	    that is required to prepare it to support bugzilla are minor changes
	    to several files.  Bugzilla is then installed in the directories 
	    dedicated to httpd.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    MySQL is already installed on <emphasis>dbserver</emphasis>, also
	    known as <emphasis>whitechuck</emphasis>, which is located on the
	    green network at 192.168.1.2.  It currently provides SPK with two databases,
	    <emphasis>spkdb</emphasis> and <emphasis>spktest</emphasis>.  All
	    that is required to make MySQL support the <emphasis>bugs</emphasis>
	    database required for bugzilla is to create a user and password
	    for the purpose. A perl script that is distributed with bugzilla
	    does the rest.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    As an adjunct to the SPK compiler daemon, bugzilla-submit must
	    be installed on the machine on which the daemon runs  We will refer to 
	    that machine as <emphasis>aspkserver</emphasis>.  In the RFPK configuration,
	    it happens to be the same machine as <emphasis>dbserver</emphasis>,
	    also known as <emphasis>whitechuck</emphasis>.  
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Bugzilla-submit is also an adjunct to the SPK runtime daemon. It
	    must be installed on the <emphasis>cspkserver</emphasis>, also
	    known as <emphasis>cluster</emphasis>, located on the green network
	    at 192.168.1.6.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title id="dbpass">Configure MySQL</title>
    <para>
      We assume that MySQL is already installed on <emphasis>dbserver</emphasis>.  The 
      document <ulink url="../mysql/mysql.html">MySQL and SPK</ulink> describes this
      installation process.
    </para>
    <para>
      On <emphasis>dbserver</emphasis>, enter the command
      <command>mysql -uroot -p</command> to start the mysql client.  Then enter the
      following four commands:
      <screen>
use mysql;

GRANT SELECT,INSERT,UPDATE,DELETE,INDEX, ALTER,CREATE,DROP,REFERENCES,
    LOCK TABLES, CREATE TEMPORARY TABLES
    ON bugs.* TO bugs@localhost IDENTIFIED BY 'secretpassword';

GRANT SELECT,INSERT,UPDATE,DELETE,INDEX, ALTER,CREATE,DROP,REFERENCES,
    LOCK TABLES, CREATE TEMPORARY TABLES
    ON bugs.* TO bugs@'%' IDENTIFIED BY 'secretpassword';

quit;
      </screen>
      This creates two users of the database <emphasis>bugs</emphasis>,
      one called <emphasis>bugs@localhost</emphasis> and the other 
      called <emphasis>bugs@'%'</emphasis>.  The first user can access
      the database from <emphasis>dbserver</emphasis>, itself.  The
      other can access it from any other host. Both users are granted
      all the privileges that bugzilla requires.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that you should replace <emphasis>secretpassword</emphasis> with
      a password that is really secret.  Note also, that the 
      <emphasis>bugs</emphasis> database does not yet exist, but will be
      created later using a program called checksetup.pl, which is part of
      the bugzilla distribution.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Configure Apache</title>
    <para>
	  Apache httpd should have already been installed on the server that will host
	  the web front-end.  In many cases, Apache httpd will be installed during the
	  installation of RedHat Linux.  If, for some reason, it is not there, install
	  the httpd rpm before proceeding.
    </para>
    <para>
	  The default Bugzilla installation was moved from <emphasis>webserver</emphasis> to
	  <emphasis>toronto</emphasis>, and can be accessed via <ulink url="http://bugzilla.rfpk.washington.edu">bugzilla.rfpk.washington.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Edit <filename>httpd.conf</filename></title>
    <para>
	On <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>,
	edit the file <filename>/etc/httpd/conf/httpd.conf</filename> to make the 
	changes described in this section.
      </para>
      <para>
	Add the following line to the file just after the paragraph describing the
	"Listen: directive, to change the port from which httpd will
	receive requests from 80 to 8081.
	<screen>
Listen 0.0.0.0:8081
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	The following are changes to lines in the file, with the original text on the 
	left of the arrow, and the new text on the right:
      <screen>
#ServerName new.host.name:80                ==>  ServerName 192.168.1.101:8081

DocumentRoot "/var/www/html"                ==>  DocumentRoot "/var/www/bugzilla"

&lt;Directory "/var/www/html"&gt;                 ==>  &lt;Directory "/var/www/bugzilla"&gt;

Options Indexes FollowSymLinks              ==>  Options +Indexes +FollowSymLinks +Includes +ExecCGI

AllowOverride None                          ==>  AllowOverride All

#ScriptAlias /cgi-bin/ "/var/www/cgi-bin/"  ==>  ScriptAlias /cgi-bin/ "var/www/bugzilla/"

#AddHandler cgi-script .cgi                 ==>  AddHandler cgi-script .cgi
      </screen>
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Empty <filename>ssl.conf</filename></title>
      <para>
	The default configuration files that are part of the RedHat
	httpd package set up a secure connection on port 443 
	as a default. We must remove the configuration directives which define
	this connection in order to avoid conflict with the SPK tomcat 
	web server, which already uses port 443.  The directives are not in
	<filename>/etc/httpd/conf/httpd.conf</filename>, but rather in
	<filename>/etc/httpd/conf.d/ssl.conf</filename>.  Since we do not need
	anything in <filename>ssl.conf</filename>, we will make a backup copy,
	then empty the file of contents.
      </para>
      <para>
	On <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>, enter the following commands:
	<screen>
cd /etc/httpd/conf.d
su
cp ssl.conf ssl.conf.bak
> ssl.conf
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Run Httpd</title>
      <para>
	We want httpd to start automatically, whenever the system boots.  Enter the
	follow commands on <emphasis>webserver</emphasis> to set up httpd to run 
	after every reboot and also to start it up now.
	<screen>
su
/sbin/chkconfig httpd on
/etc/rc.d/init.d/httpd start
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Install Perl Modules</title>
    <para>
      Bugzilla is a perl cgi application.  For it to run, it requires that a
      number of perl modules be installed on <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>
      that are not part of the standard RedHat distribution.
      The quickest way to get and install these modules is to use
      CPAN and the bugzilla <emphasis>bundle</emphasis>.  The following command
      will download the bundle and install it. You will be asked a large number
      of questions.  The default answer will generally work with the exception
      of the question concerning the <emphasis>Template</emphasis> module and
      whether or not you want to test it against the database.  In this case,
      the answer is NO!  
      <screen>
su
perl -MCPAN -e 'install "Bundle::Bugzilla"'
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Install Bugzilla</title>
    <para>
      We are now ready to install bugzilla on <emphasis>webserver</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install the Bugzilla Release</title>
    <para>
      Bugzilla can now be installed in the document root of httpd. 
      You can download a tarball from 
      <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org">bugzilla web site</ulink>.  In 
      the following example, however, it is copied from 
      <filename>/opt/download</filename> on <emphasis>whitechuck</emphasis>.
      <screen>
cd /var/www
scp 'whitechuck:/opt/download/bugzilla-2.*.tar.gz' .
tar xvzf bugzilla-2*tar.gz
rm bugzilla-2*.tar.gz
mv bugzilla* bugzilla
chgrp apache bugzilla
      </screen>
The bugzilla code and configuration files are now in the document root
of httpd.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Create a Symbolic Link to Perl</title>
      <para>
	All of the perl code in bugzilla starts with the path to perl
	itself.  This path contains an extra level of indirection, 
	perhaps to accommodate systems which have several versions of
	perl installed.  In any case, a symbolic link is required in
	order for the bugzilla perl scripts to work:
	<screen>
su
mkdir /usr/bonsaitools
mkdir /usr/bonsaitools/bin
cd /usr/bonsaitools/bin
ln -s /usr/bin/perl perl
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Create <filename>localconfig</filename></title>
      <para>
	Much of the configuration of bugzilla is performed by a program called
	checksetup.pl, which is in <filename>/var/www/bugzilla</filename>.
	This process has multiple stages. In the first stage, we run 
	checksetup.pl, and it examines the environment in which it is running.
	Tnen it creates as output a file called <filename>localconfig</filename>.
	Next we edit <filename>localconfig</filename> to provide additional
	information that checksetup.pl will need, but which it could not 
	deduce from the environment. After saving the modified
	<filename>localconfig</filename>,
	we again run checksetup.pl to
	configure the system.  This should complete the configuration, but
	if it is also possible that checksetup.pl will find inconsistencies
	in our setup and will request additional information or changes.
      </para>
      <screen>
su
cd /var/www/bugzilla
./checksetup.pl
      </screen>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Edit <filename>localconfig</filename></title>
      <para>
	Now edit <filename>/var/www/buzilla/localconfig</filename> to have the
	following values, rather than the defaults that were assigned by
	checksetup.pl:
	<screen>
$index_html = 1;
$webservergroup = "apache";
$db_host = "dbserver";         # where is the database?
$db_pass = 'secretpassword';
	</screen>
	Note that <emphasis>secretpassword</emphasis> should be replaced by the 
	password that you assigned when you added the <emphasis>bugs</emphasis>
	user to MySQL, <link linkend="dbpass">above</link>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Run checksetup.pl</title>
      <para>
	Run checksetup.pl again, so that it can process the additional information
	that you provided in <filename>localconfig</filename>.
      <screen>
su
cd /var/www/bugzilla
./checksetup.pl
      </screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	You will be asked to provide the email address of the administrator
	and a password.  Give your own email address and a good password,
	so that you will be permitted to use the bugzilla administrative
	screens to do the final configuration.
      </para>
      <para>
	With this run of checksetup.pl,
	the <emphasis>bugs</emphasis> database will be created on 
	<emphasis>dbserver</emphasis>, an <filename>index.html</filename>
	file will be created in the apache httpd root directory, and various 
	file system permissions will be set so that apache httpd can 
	access them properly.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="usersect">
      <title id="adduser">Use Bugzilla to Configure Bugzilla</title>
      <para>
	You should now be able to access your bugzilla installation via
	your web browser. You will log in as the administrator, using
	a password that must remain secret.  Bugzilla does not use 
	secure connections, however, hence you should
	<emphasis>only administer bugzilla from a workstation
	  located behind the firewall.</emphasis>
	The url to use, therefore, is
	<ulink url="http://192.168.1.101:8081">http://192.168.1.101:8081</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
	When you click the above link, your browser should arrive at the
	"Bugzilla Main Page" for your installation.  At the lower left-hand
	corner of the page is a link to 
	<emphasis>Log In</emphasis>.  After logging in, your browser should
	take you to the query page.  At the bottom of the page is a set
	of links which, because you are the administrator, will include those
	which allow you to edit parameters, users, and products.
      </para>
      <para>
	Be sure to configure the following:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Users: at a minimum, add the developer responsible for ASPK
	      and the developer responsible for CSPK, because these will
	      be required for the configuration of <emphasis>Components</emphasis>,
	      below. The user <emphasis>rfpkbugs@u.washington.edu</emphasis> must
	      also be entered. Assign good passwords to each of these
	      users, and remember their values.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Products: add SPK
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Components: for SPK, add ASPK and CSPK, at a minimum, because
	      they will be needed by bugzilla-submit.  For each component,
	      designate one of the developers that you entered as users
	      as the owner.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Parameters: among the parameters that can be set, are a number of
	      templates for email that bugzilla sends to users for various
	      purposes.  In each of these which has something like
	      <emphasis>Bugzilla Daemon</emphasis> as the 
	      <emphasis>From:</emphasis> address, replace it with 
	      <emphasis>rfpkbugs@u.washington.edu</emphasis>.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      You should also enter <emphasis>your email address</emphasis> as 
	      <emphasis>maintainer</emphasis> and
	      <emphasis>http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu:8081</emphasis>
	      as <emphasis>urlbase</emphasis>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Install bugzilla-submit on aspkserver and cspkserver</title>
    <para>
      Normally, defects are reported to bugzilla via the web interface.  An 
      add-on program, called bugzilla-submit, enables defects to be reported
      from the command line.  Installing bugzilla-submit makes it possible for
      the compiler daemon and the runtime daemon to automatically submit
      defects to bugzilla if an instance of the compiler or of the runtime
      dies.  
    </para>
    <para>
      At RFPK, the compiler daemon runs on <emphasis>aspkserver</emphasis> and
      the runtime runs on <emphasis>cspkserver</emphasis>, which are different
      machines.  Bugzilla-submit must be installed on both machines.  It is
      possible to install the whole of SPK on a single server.  In that case,
      it would only be necessary to install bugzilla-submit once.  It is 
      also possible that a runtime daemon would run on each of a number of
      computational machines.  In that case, bugzilla-submit would need
      to be installed on each of them.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following sections describe the installation on one machine.
      Simply repeat the instructions for each machine where bugzilla-submit
      is needed.
    </para>
    <para>
      The software can be downloaded from the 
      <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org">bugzilla web site</ulink>.  In the
      following instructions, however, it is copied from 
      <emphasis>whitechuck</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install Python</title>
      <para>
	Bugzilla-submit is a python application, which requires python version
	2.3 or later.  If either the machine does not have python or has a version
	older than 2.3, it will first be necessary to install python.
	<screen>
cd /tmp
scp 'whitechuck:/opt/download/Python-2.3*bz2' .
tar xvjf Python*bz2
cd Python*
./configure
make
su 
make install
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install bugzilla-submit</title>
      <screen>
cd /tmp
scp 'whitechuck:/opt/download/bugzilla-submit*gz' .
tar xvzf bugzilla-submit*gz
cd bugzilla-submit
su
cp bugzilla-submit /usr/local/bin/bugzilla-submit
      </screen>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configure <filename>.netrc</filename></title>
      <para>
	<screen>
su
cd
emacs .netrc
	</screen>
Using your favorite editor (you could use vi, for example,
rather than emacs in the command, above), insert the following
	<screen>
machine         "http://192.168.1.101:8081/"
login           rfpkbugs@u.washington.edu
password        <emphasis>secretpassword</emphasis>
	</screen>
	Provide as a password the password that you gave to
	the bugzilla user
	<emphasis>rfpkbugs@u.washington.edu</emphasis>
	when you added that user as described 
	<link linkend="adduser">above</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
	The <filename>.netrc</filename> file provides information
	required by bugzilla-submit in order for its connection
	request to be accepted by bugzilla.  The 
	<emphasis>machine></emphasis> field must agree with the
	a value defined in the spkcmpd.pl and spkrund.pl, the
	compiler daemon and runtime daemon, respectively.  If
	the machine that hosts bugzilla is changed, the new IP
	address must be changed in both daemons and all .netrc
	files.
      </para>
      <para>
	The <filename>.netrc</filename> file will not be read if 
	the mode bits allow access to anyone but the owner.  If
	<command>ls -l .netrc</command> does not show -rw-------,
	set mode properly as follows:
	<screen>
su
cd
chmod 0600 .netrc
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  DOCTYPE DocBook uw Bugzilla articleinfo revhistory revnumber
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  authorinitials revremark RFPK SPK perl RDBMS MySQL httpd MDA
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  bugzilla orderedlist listitem webserver Redhat dbserver url
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  whitechuck spkdb spktest spkcmpd aspkserver spkrund ulink lt
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  cspkserver mysql uroot secretpassword checksetup RedHat conf
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  ServerName DocumentRoot FollowSymLinks ExecCGI AllowOverride
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  ScriptAlias cgi AddHandler ssl cd su mv CPAN MCPAN tmp cp gz
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  xvzf chgrp mkdir ln localconfig html webservergroup usersect
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  adduser itemizedlist ASPK CSPK usrbase scp bz xvjf netrc IP
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  linkend
 -->
