<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
     "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>The Benefits of Open Source</title>
 <articleinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Alan</firstname>
      <surname>Westhagen</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<jobtitle>Software Architect</jobtitle>
	<jobtitle>RFPK Software Team Leader</jobtitle>
      </affiliation>
    </author>  
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>July 14, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  <abstract>
      <para>
	The System for Population Kinetics (SPK) is software being developed
	by the RFPK Laboratory, in the Bioengineering Department of the 
	University of Washington, under grant <emphasis>P41 EB-001975</emphasis>
	from the National Institutes
	of Health (NIH) of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.	
	This white paper presents the rationale for the choice by RFPK of an open
	source development and distribution model for this software.
      </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      With the traditional model of software distribution,
      source code was assumed to be
      private information.  Software was distributed as binary object code,
      which would reveal its inner structure only through very difficult 
      analysis of CPU instruction sequences. Users or third-party developers who wanted to
      modify the software were constrained from doing so by intellectual property laws,
      even when their efforts in reverse engineering were otherwise
      successful.
    </para>
    <para>
      The open source distribution model reverses the old assumptions.
      Source code is not secret. A copy of the source code is always published
      as part of the distribution package.  Anyone who has a copy of the code
      is authorized to redistribute it.
      Anyone is free to modify the code.  If they do so, they are under no
      obligation to share their enhancements with anyone.  If, however, they
      distribute a modified version of the original, they must include in the
      distribution the altered source code.  Co-development is strongly
      encouraged.
    </para>
    <para>
      Although this white paper will be primarily concerned with practical
      considerations, it is appropriate at the onset to acknowledge the equally
      important philosophical dimension. In a profound manner, open source 
      mirrors the academic ideal of free exchange of ideas through publication
      and discourse, and the furthering of knowledge as a cooperative endeavor
      in ways that closed source does not.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Goals</title>
    <para>
      In the interest of developing this rationale in a top-down manner, it
      is best to start with the purpose of the software itself.
    </para>
    <anchor id="goal"/>
    <para>
      SPK exists <emphasis>to improve the quality and expand the application of population
      kinetic modeling in biomedical research.
    </emphasis></para>
    <para>
      Important practical benefits will be 
      a reduction in the cost of developing drugs, as well as improvements
      in their safety and effectiveness.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Case for Free Beer</title>
    <para>
      Open source software is often described as <emphasis>free</emphasis> software.
      What is meant is <emphasis>free, as in freedom,</emphasis> and not
      <emphasis>free, as in free beer</emphasis>.  The latter definition is,
      nevertheless, highly relevant to the distribution of SPK.
      Some of the potential users of SPK have the resources to pay handsomely
      for critical software.  This is true, one would suppose, of the
      pharmaceutical industry. 
      Drug companies, however, will not buy software which has not already established
      its credibility by use in the broader biomedical research community.  For
      this reason, RFPK has chosen a strategy of setting the purchase price of
      SPK to zero, in order to maximize the number of users.
    </para>
    <para>
      It could be argued that by giving away its software RFPK is foregoing income
      which might be used to hire more programmers, to make the project 
      self-sustaining, or even to provide a profit.  There is no guarantee of success
      in the software business,
      however.  Many firms have produced excellent software but have nevertheless
      failed for marketing reasons, and their software has disappeared along with them.
      RFPK believes that wide adoption of its software and its long-term viability
      can be achieved without subjecting the project to the vagaries of the market.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Case Against Free Binaries</title>
    <para>
      As an alternative to giving away source code, RFPK considered giving away 
      object code instead.  There are several reasons that this option was 
      rejected:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Open source greatly reduces the cost of developing and distributing 
	    complex software, such as SPK.  (This advantage will be described
	    in subsequent sections.)  If RFPK were to exclude source code from
	    its distribution, it would become ineligible for most of the benefits
	    of open source development.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <anchor id="risk"/>
	    In addition to a workstation and an Internet connection, an SPK user
	    needs access to an SPK service provider.  The service provider offers
	    a web site, servers and a computational cluster.  RFPK is itself a service provider.
	    For the project to achieve the goal of wide adoption, there must be 
	    many more SPK service providers.  
	    A service provider might be embedded in an academic research group such as 
	    RFPK.  It might be part of the IT department of a pharmaceutical company.
	    It might be one of the offerings of a consulting or computer services firm.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Providing a service such as SPK represents a considerable investment,
	    especially if a powerful computational cluster is involved.
	    Before making this commitment, a potential service provider would want some assurance
	    that SPK would continue to evolve and to be maintained.  RFPK is a first rate
	    organization, with excellent prospects for obtaining a renewal of its current grant
	    and for obtaining additional grants.  Even so, some might see the small
	    size of RFPK as a risk factor.  
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    With open source, all interested parties have access to source code.  In
	    the unlikely event that RFPK would no longer be able to continue 
	    the development of SPK, other organizations would be positioned to step in
	    to fill the gap. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Case for Open Source</title>
    <para>
      Open Source provides RFPK with the freedom it needs to develop a complex
      product on a modest budget.  
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Freedom to Include the Work of Others</title>
      <para>
	SPK includes many other pieces of software, some of which represent much more 
	development effort than the code that RFPK itself has written.
	The incorporated modules include:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>MySQL</emphasis> relational database management system
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Tomcat</emphasis> web server
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>NetBeans</emphasis> interactive development environment
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>GNU RCS</emphasis> revision control system
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>Atlas</emphasis> (Automatically Tuned Linear Algebra Software)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>CppAd</emphasis> c++ automatic differentiation library
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis>GNU Operating System</emphasis>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	All of this software can be freely distributed as part of a system that
	is open source.  There is no need to negotiate with the copyright holders
	over price or conditions. Inclusion of closed source software always 
	requires negotiation preceded by cost and benefit analysis.
      </para>
      <para>
	Consider for example the MySQL relational database management system.  As
	part of an open source application, it can be freely distributed without the
	payment of any royalties.  When part of a proprietary system, however, it
	can only be distributed under a commercial license, which requires the 
	payment of fees similar to those charged for other database management systems.
	If SPK were not open source, it would be necessary to do a cost and benefit
	comparison between MySQL and similar systems, such as Oracle, DB2, 
	SyBase and SQL-Server.  It would then be necessary to negotiate prices for
	placing the software on development machines, test machines and, finally,
	on the customers' machines.  The price of the database management system would be 
	loaded on top of the price of SPK, making the total package more expensive
	for the customer to acquire.  Having to deal with business issues such
	as these would inevitably draw resources away from development.
      </para>
      <para>
	The SPK service is delivered over the world-wide-web.
	MySQL, Tomcat, and the GNU operating system are widely used in that environment.
	Although Microsoft products dominate on the desktop and in the office, 
	open source products dominate the Internet.  SPK concedes nothing in terms
	of quality or usability by including these excellent products.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Freedom to Share the Work with Others</title>
      <para>
	With closed source, a software company is always extremely protective 
	of its intellectual property.  It is very rare that a company opens its source code
	to outsiders, and even then it is not to enable them to modify the 
	code, but only to better understand how it works or how to interface
	to it.  They usually expect to be paid for this privilege and to be indemnified
	in case their secrets are leaked to third parties.
      </para>
      <para>
	With open source, the situation is reversed.  Every recipient of the 
	software has a right to the source code and the right to modify it.
	There is no need to negotiate price and conditions.  There is no
	concern over the leaking of information that is already public.
	Anyone with the software is a potential co-developer.
      </para>
      <para>
	The tools that are used to develop open source products are themselves
	open source.  The cost of obtaining these tools is low or non-existent.
	Anyone with a Linux computer, for example, already has most of these
	tools installed on her machine or can easily download them from the
	Internet.  This is another way in which the threshold for becoming
	a co-developer is very low.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Freedom from Proprietary Lock-In</title>
      <para>
	The strategy to make it difficult or impossible for consumers of computer
	technology to change
	system vendor is known as proprietary lock-in,  At one time, this strategy
	was pursued successfully by all major computer manufacturers. Software developers were
	enlisted, whether willingly or unwillingly, in this endeavor via the
	means of the <emphasis>application programming interface (API).</emphasis>
	To develop software to run on the systems of a particular computer company, a developer
	had to use the  API of that vendor. The software would run on
	the systems of that company and none other.  This strategy partitioned
	the world of software development along API lines.  Because of the
	intentional incompatibility of the APIs, most software houses were forced
	to develop software for the platform of a single vendor. It would then be 
	impossible for consumers who purchased the software to switch computer
	manufacturers.  They were locked in and could no longer
	benefit from competition between vendors.
      </para>
      <para>
	The Unix operating system was revolutionary, not because it was more
	powerful, or more efficient, or had better features, but because it was
	<emphasis>portable</emphasis>.  Within a few years of its creation at
	AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories, it had been modified to run on most of the 
	computer processors available at the time.  Software development needed 
	no longer to be <emphasis>balkanized.</emphasis>  Systems written to the
	Unix API could be easily ported to any Unix system, whether the hardware
	came from IBM, Digital, Hewlett Packard, Sun, SGI, etc.  Consumers loved it, because
	they now had the option of changing hardware vendors.  
	The old-line computer manufacturers hated it, and
	did everything in their power to impede the process of migration to Unix.
      </para>
      <para>
	By the mid 1990's, the battle between Unix and the old proprietary
	operating systems was over, with Unix the victor. Those computer companies 
	which had first opposed Unix and then had impeded its adoption were now
	solidly committed to delivering Unix on their hardware and developing
	applications using the Unix API.  At the same time, these companies
	underwent a transformation from being primarily manufacturers to also
	being systems integrators and consultants.  In this new environment, an
	operating system which could run on any hardware made integration of
	systems much easier.
      </para>
      <para>
	At the same time that Unix was consolidating its dominance for the large
	and medium sized computers used as Internet servers, database servers,
	and enterprise application servers, another force was at work.  Microsoft
	recognized that desktop computing and office automation would be the 
	major growth area for information technologies.  By developing
	Windows as an operating system that could provide an easy-to-use
	graphical user interface for the desktop and a platform for office
	automation, Microsoft asserted its dominance at the low end of the
	computer spectrum.  
      </para>
      <para>
	SPK is a complex system, made of a number of components.  These can be
	divided between the <emphasis>server side</emphasis>,
	which runs on server machines and high performance computing (HPC)
	clusters, and the <emphasis>client side</emphasis>, which runs on the
	end-user's workstation or laptop.
      </para>
      <para>
	For the server-side, 
	there are today for all practical purposes, only two APIs for software developers
	to choose from.  The Unix API is supported by all Unix and Unix-compatible
	systems, including Linux and Apple Macintosh OS-10.  The Windows API is supported
	by the Microsoft Windows operating system.  The two are incompatible.
      </para>
      <para>	
	The choice of server-side API determines the processor architectures on which the
	software will run.  
	Programs written to the Unix API can be installed on nearly every 
	processor architecture in existence, including Intel Pentium and Itanium,
	but also Sparc, Alpha, PowerPC and IBM Mainframes.  Software written to the Windows API
	runs only on Pentium and Itanium.
      </para>
      <para>
	The choice of API also determines the operating system that must be used.  For SPK, this 
	turns out to be of prime importance, because almost all 
	HPC clusters run Unix or Unix-compatible operating systems rather than Windows.
	SPK is developed to the open source GNU version of the Unix API. This is
	the most portable of all APIs.  This choice enables SPK to run on
	practically all clusters available. 
      </para>
      <para>
	For the client side,
	many end-users of SPK prefer to use Windows as the operating system for
	their workstations and laptops.  This is a choice
	that RFPK respects.  Proprietary lock-in is
	avoided through the use of Java, the 
	<emphasis>write once, run anywhere</emphasis> technology,
	which allows the client side of SPK to run not only on top of Windows,
	but also on Apple Macintosh OS-10, Linux or Unix, depending on the
	user's preference.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Impact of Open Source</title>
    <para>
      Up to this point, this paper has focused primarily on how the
      decision to develop and distribute SPK as open source affects
      RFPK itself.  This decision also affects other constituencies, 
      including end users, service providers, consultants and software
      houses.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>End Users</title>
      <para>
	The impact on end users is positive and unambiguous.  They 
	obtain the client software for free and the service at a price that
	should be competitive because of the low threshold of entry for 
	service providers.  In fact, computer-savvy end users can obtain
	the entire SPK package for free and install it on their own hardware
	if that is preferable to using a service provider.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Service Providers</title>
      <para>
	Service providers can download SPK for free and install it on their
	hardware.  Because RFPK has chosen to develop SPK using open
	source GNU tools, it is possible to install the software on just
	about any hardware that the service provider has available.  The
	requirement that the operating system be either Unix or a
	Unix-compatible system such as Linux or Mac-OS10 is not a barrier
	for most service providers, who already have in-house Unix 
	expertise.  As discussed <link linkend="risk">above</link>, the
	the fact that open source distribution creates a community of individuals and
	organizations that would continue the development of maintenance
	should RFPK go out of existence, eliminates that risk to service providers.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Consultants</title>
      <para>
	SPK can be a real boon to consultants, especially if they choose to
	become service providers.  Because SPK is a web based service, it is
	easy to differentiate a particular SPK from others through specialization
	of the web site and through the provision of proprietary PK models.
	It is important to note that models are not part of SPK.  They are, 
	rather, the intellectual property of the person or organization
	which develops them.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Software Houses</title>
      <para>
	There remains opportunity for developers of 
	proprietary software to add value to SPK by replacing entire modules.
	Architecturally, SPK can be viewed as a cooperating group of 
	loosely-coupled independent processes.  The interfaces between these
	processes are well documented.  A software house could, for example, replace the 
	SPK client program with its own proprietary client, which might feature a 
	different type of graphical user interface or which might integrate seamlessly
	with its other products.  A software house that specialized in getting the
	most out of computational clusters might develop a proprietary replacement
	for the SPK run-time daemon which might do a superior job of optimizing
	work flow.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para>
      In conclusion, open source is the right choice for RFPK, because it 
      significantly enhances its ability to achieve its 
      <link linkend="goal">goal</link>, given its limited resources.  
      Other groups benefit as well, because open source creates a community
      to which all constituencies can contribute and from which all can
      draw benefits.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  xml DOCTYPE DocBook uw articleinfo firstname Westhagen RFPK
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  jobtitle revhistory revnumber authorinitials revremark SPK
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  itemizedlist listitem SSP SSPs MySQL NetBeans CppAd SyBase
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  SQL HPC linkend MDA API APIs SGI Itanium Sparc PowerPC
 -->
