<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>Keeping Linux Up-To-Date</title>
 <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>May 30, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>July 25, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Updated for systems that do not dual-boot</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  <abstract>
      <para>
	It is important to keep the Software Team's Linux workstations
	up-to-date, with security fixes and bug fixes.  This document
	describes the procedure for updating a workstation via
	the Internet.
      </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      For each of the Software Team's Linux workstations, RFPK has
      purchased a subscription to use the RedHat Network (RHN) for keeping
      Linux up-to-date.  This subscription also enables priority
      downloads of any of the large number of software packages that
      are offered by RedHat.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is important to make use of RHN at frequent intervals, to
      keep your system current.  Updating does not have to take
      much time away from other work.  While the process is 
      going on, most of the time is spent in data transfer.
      During that period, you can also be using your
      workstation for other things.  Let the files download and
      then go back to the updating process when all the files
      are there.
    </para>
    <para>
      With the exception of a kernel update, there is no
      need to reboot after an update is complete.  With the
      kernel, you first need to make a new boot diskette, and
      then use that to boot.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Using the RHN Alert Notification Tool</title>
    <para>
      On the panel at the bottom of your desktop screen, you
      should have a small circle with a check-mark in it.  This
      is the icon for the alert notification applet.  When it is red, there
      are updates available to packages installed on your system.
      When it is blue, all packages are up-to-date.  Green
      means that updates are in progress.
    </para>
    <para>
      Whenever you notice that the alert notification icon is red, and
      you have a few spare moments, click on it and then click the
      <guibutton>Launch up2date</guibutton> button. It is most
      convenient to do this with an empty workspace
      on the screen, so that the up2date windows do not get mixed
      up with your other work.
    </para>
    <para>
      The up2date wizard presents a list of "channels".  Select the
      channel which corresponds to the release of Linux installed
      on your workstation.  Generally, there will be only one 
      choice, because up2date is smart enough to know this.
    </para>
    <para>
      The wizard will then refresh its own information about any
      updates available for your system.  It will give you a list
      to choose from.  In the case of kernel updates, ask 
      Alan Westhagen first whether or not that update is worth
      performing.  For everything else, just select them all.
    </para>
    <para>
      From that point on, just let up2date do its work.  
      Occasionally check back.  Since up2date is interactive,
      it may be waiting for an acknowledgment from you.  
    </para>
    <para>
      When up2date says that it is finished, you are done, as
      well.  You do not have to reboot, unless you updated
      the kernel. The next section discusses what to do in 
      that case,
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>After a Kernel Update</title>
    <para>
      If you boot Linux from the hard drive, there is nothing more
      to do.  The next time you boot, the machine will come up on
      the new version of Linux.
    </para>
    <para>
      If your machine is dual-booted and you use a diskette to
      boot onto Linux, you will need to make a new boot diskette and
      a new backup boot diskette.  Here is the procedure to follow.
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Determine the version number of the new kernel.
	    The <command>rpm</command> command can be used to list 
	    all packages installed on your workstation, and 
	    <command>grep</command> can be used to filter out
	    every line that does not contain the text
	    "kernel-" followed by a digit:
	    <screen>
rpm -qa | grep kernel-[0-9]	    
	    </screen>
	    The kernel package with the largest version number
	    is the new one. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You probably have three boot diskettes.  Two of the
	    diskettes are for the version you currently are
	    running.  The third is for the version that you
	    ran previously.  Take that third diskette and 
	    insert it in your diskette drive.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    As root, execute the <command>mkbootdisk</command>
	    command, giving the version number as argument.  For
	    example, if you just installed the package
	    <filename>kernel-2.4.20-13.8</filename>, you would
	    enter the following command lines:
	    <screen>
su
/sbin/mkbootdisk 2.4.20-13.8 
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Repeat the previous two steps, in order to make
	    a backup copy of the boot diskette.  Use one of the
	    two diskettes containing the version you are currently
	    running.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Boot onto the new kernel, using one of the 
	    diskettes you have just made.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Removing Redundant Kernels</title>
    <para>
      You only need to have two kernels installed: the
      current kernel and the previous kernel.  To
      reduce clutter, you can remove old kernel packages.
      Suppose that the 
      <command>rpm -qa | grep kernel-[0-9]</command>
      command line returned the names of three kernel
      packages, and that
      <filename>kernel-2.4.14.8.0</filename> was the
      oldest of them.  To remove that package,
      use these commands:
      <screen>
su
rpm -ev kernel-2.4.14.8.0	      
      </screen>
      You can get a list of all kernels installed by using the
      rpm query function:
      <screen>
rpm -qa | grep kernel
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Downloading Packages from RHN</title>
    <para>
      When the Software Team workstations were originally
      set up for Linux, a large number of packages were
      installed, especially in the area of tools for software
      development.  There are, nevertheless, many additional
      packages available.
    </para>
    <para>
      For the great number of packages that are put together by
      RedHat, RHN is the most convenient as well as the most
      secure source. Just go to the 
      <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/software/rhn/">RHN</ulink>
      site, login, and click on the 
      <guimenuitem>software</guimenuitem> button.  You should
      then be able to find packages for the release of RedHat
      Linux that you are running.
    </para>
    <para>
      If RHN doesn't have it, there are a number of other 
      sources for rpm packages.  A good place to look is
      <ulink url="http://www.rpmfind.net/">rpmfind</ulink>,
      which is mirrored by speakeasy.net, in Seattle.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  DOCTYPE DocBook articleinfo revhistory revnumber revremark
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  authorinitials RFPK RedHat RHN guibutton Westhagen listitem
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  orderedlist qa mkbootdisk su ev ulink url guimenuitem
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  rpmfind
 -->
