<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>Web Server HOWTO</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>February 26, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>March 23, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Modified to use four instances of Tomcat</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	Because Spk provides its services via the World Wide Web, an important
	component of the overall system is the web server.  This document
	describes the installation and configuration of web server software
	to support Spk.
      </para>
      <para>
	To complete the configuration for secure https connections, you will
	need two authentication certificates.  If you do not have these
	certificates, it might be a good idea to obtain them before proceeding
	with the web server configuration.  See the
	<ulink url="../authentication/authentication.html">
	  Authentication and Encryption HOWTO
	</ulink> for details.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The client component of Spk, called the Model Design Agent (MDA), is
      written in the Java language.  It communicates with the rest of the
      system via the Internet, using the <emphasis>http</emphasis>
      and <emphasis>https</emphasis> protocols.  On the
      server side of this communication is a web server, which is software
      that supports World Wide Web functionality and runs continuously in a server machine.
      The fact that the MDA is a Java application makes it very desirable
      that the components that communicate with the MDA from the server side
      be also written in Java. Server-side Java components such as those
      in Spk are known as <emphasis>Java servlets</emphasis>. A closely related
      technology, called 
      <emphasis>Java Server Pages (JSP)</emphasis>, is an extensible set of 
      extensions to HTML which can be used to generate servlets.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to run servlets and JSP within a web server, software known as
      a <emphasis>servlet/JSP container</emphasis> is required.  Tomcat, a
      free product of the Catalina project, which in turn is part of the
      Jakarta project sponsored by Apache, the leading developer of web
      server software, serves this purpose for Spk.  Tomcat can be added
      to an Apache web server, in which case it provides only the 
      servlet/JSP container function, or it can be installed as a complete
      stand-alone web server and servlet/JSP container.  For the purposes of Spk,
      the latter is the simpler solution.
    </para>
    <para>
      The rest of this document describes the installation and configuration
      of tomcat for Spk.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="INSTANCES">
    <title>Tomcat Instances and Web Applications</title>
    <para>
      It is possible to run several copies of Tomcat simultaneously.  Each 
      independently running copy is called an <emphasis>instance</emphasis>.
      As will be explained, shortly, an Spk installation requires four
      Tomcat instances.
    </para>
    <para>
      A Tomcat instance expects to find its configuration information, as well
      as its applications, in a file hierarchy of a
      certain, predetermined structure.  One of the directories, called 
      <filename>webapps</filename>, contains one or more web applications, 
      also known as <emphasis>contexts</emphasis>.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Like all web servers, Tomcat receives requests formatted either to the
      standards of the <emphasis>http</emphasis> protocol or to the
      encrypted <emphasis>https</emphasis> protocol.  The latter is also
      known as the <emphasis>secure socket layer (SSL)</emphasis>.  A 
      Tomcat instance can designate one tcp port for http and another one for
      https.  Most often, port 80 is used for http and port 443 for https, but
      any other port numbers can be used instead.  For Spk, we use 
      80 and 443 for the production ports; 8080 and 8443 for test ports.
    </para>
    <para>
      From a reliability point of view, it is absolutely essential to have a web
      for testing that is identical to the 
      web server used for production.  The simplest way to achieve this is
      to have a production instance and a test instance of the same software
      running on the same machine.  This is the approach that we take with
      Spk.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most of the Spk web site must be run in the secure SSL mode, in order to
      protect the privacy of patient data and proprietary nature of some of the
      PK models.  We absolutely do not want users to be able to access certain
      web pages using only the ordinary http protocol.  With Tomcat,
      unfortunately, there is no way (or at least none that we have discovered)
      to keep a user from accessing, with http, the pages intended only for https, if
      both http and https ports are configured for the same instance.  For this
      reason, an Spk installation requires four instances, rather than two.
    </para>
    <para>
      The four instances are:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Production Instance, receiving http requests on port 80
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Production SSL Instance, receiving https requests on port 443
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Test Instance, receiving http request on port 8080
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Test SSL Instance, receiving https requests on port 8443
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      When changes are made to a Java web application, it is very easy to deploy
      the modified application to a Tomcat instance if the application is organized
      in a certain predetermined hierarchy of directories and files. A special 
      compressed archive format, known as a Web Archive (war), has been defined
      for compressing such an archive into a single file, for easy transport and
      storage.  These files normally carry a <filename>.war</filename> file
      name suffix, and are very similar to the more familiar
      <filename>.zip</filename>, <filename>.tar</filename> and, especially,
      <filename>.jar</filename> files.
    </para>
    <para>
      When a <filename>.war</filename> file is copied into the
      <filename>webapps</filename> directory of a Tomcat instance, it is 
      automatically parsed, translated, compiled and linked by Tomcat itself, replacing
      the existing version of the application, without any need to interrupt
      operations.  
    </para>
    <para>
      The web portion of Spk is divided into two web applications:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>init</emphasis>, which consists of static content, informative
	    to everyone with an interest in Spk.  The authorship and maintenance of
	    this application is primarily the responsibility of the 
	    RFPK Science Team.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>user</emphasis>, which consists of dynamic content, including
	    user login, MDA launch, status and historical information about the 
	    jobs of a particular user.  The <emphasis>user</emphasis> application
	    is the responsibility of the RFPK Software Team.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Both the <emphasis>init</emphasis> context and the <emphasis>user</emphasis>
      context are accessible exclusively via https. 
      The archives <filename>init.war</filename> and 
      <filename>user.war</filename> must be installed in the 
      <filename>webapps</filename> directory of either of the production SSL
      instance or the test SSL instance, but never in the other two instances.
    </para>
    <para>
      The two non-SSL instances contain only a trivial application which 
      redirects the user's browser to the <emphasis>init</emphasis> context on
      the associated SSL instance.  This redirection is transparent and 
      immediate, and should not normally be noticed by the user. The 
      redirection, however, allows users to initiate contact with Spk via the standard 
      non-secure URL 
      <ulink url="http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu">
	http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu
      </ulink>.  
      This application can be found in the <filename>ROOT</filename> context in the
      <filename>webapps</filename> directory of the production and test non-SSL
      instances.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Installing Tomcat</title>
    <para>
      In a terminal window, as an ordinary user, download the tomcat tarball from whitechuck,
      then <command>su</command> to become <emphasis>root</emphasis>:
      <screen>
scp 'whitechuck:/opt/download/jakarta-tomcat*.tar.gz' .
su
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      If you do not already have a directory called <filename>/usr/local/tomcat</filename>,
      create one:
      <screen>
mkdir /usr/local/tomcat
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Move the tarball to <filename>/usr/local/tomcat</filename>, and expand it:
      <screen>
mv jakarta-tomcat*.tar.gz /usr/local/tomcat
cd /usr/local/tomcat
tar xvzf *
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Defining Environment Variables</title>
    <para>
      It is convenient to define an environment variable, CATALINA_HOME,
      which contains the path to the directory in which tomcat is installed.
      Edit your <filename>~/.bash_profile</filename> file, adding lines to
      define CATALINA_HOME and to export it.
    </para>
    <para>
      For example, suppose that the tarball expanded to
      <filename>jakarta-tomcat-5.0.18</filename>. Then you would add these lines
      to <filename>~/.bash_profile</filename>:
      <screen>
CATALINA_HOME=/usr/local/tomcat/jakarta-tomcat-5.0.18
export CATALINA_HOME
      </screen>
      After saving your modified <filename>~/.bash_profile</filename>,
      restart your desktop by logging out and then logging back in again.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Creating Four Run-Time Instances</title>
    <para>
      In this section, we will set things up so that four independent 
      instances of tomcat can run simultaneously. As explained 
      <link linkend="INSTANCES">above</link>, the four instances are
      production, test, production SSL and test SSL.
    </para>
    <para>
      The following steps will create the file hierarchies for the two instances:
      <screen>
su
cd $CATALINA_HOME/..
mkdir instance
cd instance
mkdir prod
mkdir test
mkdir prodssl
mkdir testssl
cp -r $CATALINA_HOME/conf prod
cp -r $CATALINA_HOME/conf test
cp -r $CATALINA_HOME/conf prodssl
cp -r $CATALINA_HOME/conf testssl
cd ../prod
mkdir logs temp webapps work
cd test
mkdir logs temp webapps work
cd ../prodssl
mkdir logs temp webapps work
cd testssl
mkdir logs temp webapps work
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="PERMIT">
    <title>Configuring User Groups and Permissions</title>
    <para>
      At present, it is not possible to run the production instance
      or the production SSL instance with any user other than
      root, because only root can open ports with numbers less
      than 1024. It might be more secure to run under an ordinary
      user, as does Apache, but that capability is not yet available.
      On the other hand, Tomcat may be less vulnerable to certain
      exploits, such as buffer overflows, because of Java's built-in
      protection of against such problems.
    </para>
    <para>
      Although root must be the tomcat process owner,
      it is preferable for its files to belong to a user
      or users other than root.  That way, ordinary users can be given the authority
      to modify these files without having to know the root password.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that in the following, we are using a concept called 
      <emphasis>user private groups.</emphasis>  We use the same set of conventions
      for ownership and permissions in the CVS repository.  For additional
      information, see the RedHat Enterprise Linux 
      <ulink url="https://www.redhat.com/docs/manuals/enterprise/RHEL-3-Manual/ref-guide/s1-users-groups-private-groups.html">
	Reference Guide
      </ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      First we create a user and a group. The user <emphasis>tomcat</emphasis>
      will be the owner of the files, while the group <emphasis>webadmin</emphasis>
      will have group access to them.
      <screen>
su
/usr/sbin/useradd -r tomcat
/usr/sbin/groupadd -r webadmin
/usr/bin/gpasswd -a tomcat webadmin
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      At this point, you should also add <emphasis>your user name</emphasis>
      to the webadmin group:
      <screen>
/usr/bin/gpasswd -a <emphasis>your-user-name</emphasis> webadmin
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Now set permissions on the file hierarchies for the instances:
      <screen>
cd $CATALINA_HOME/../instance
chown -R tomcat.webadmin *
find . -type d -exec chmod 2775 {} \;
find . -type f -exec chmod g+rw {} \;
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Configuring the Instances</title>
    <para>
      In each instance,
      we need to make changes to <filename>server.xml</filename>, which is the principal
      configuration file for tomcat.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Changing the Shutdown Port</title>
      <para>
	In the default configuration, tomcat receives shutdown requests on
	port 8005.  We will leave 8005 as the shutdown value for the test
	server, but select different ports for each of the other instances.
      </para>
      <para>
	You should be able to make the following changes as an ordinary user,
	assuming that you have set up your permissions correctly, as describe
	<link linkend="PERMIT">above</link>.
	<screen>
cd /usr/local/tomcat/instance
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Before editing, each of the files <filename>*/conf/server.xml</filename>
	will look like this:
	<screen>
&lt;Server port="8005" shutdown="SHUTDOWN" debug="0"&gt;
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Edit <filename>prod/conf/server.xml </filename> to look like this:
	<screen>
&lt;Server port="8006" shutdown="SHUTDOWN" debug="0"&gt;
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Edit <filename>testssl/conf/server.xml </filename> to look like this:
	<screen>
&lt;Server port="8007" shutdown="SHUTDOWN" debug="0"&gt;
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Edit <filename>prodssl/conf/server.xml </filename> to look like this:
	<screen>
&lt;Server port="8008" shutdown="SHUTDOWN" debug="0"&gt;
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring Request Ports for the Instances</title>
      <para>
	In the <filename>server.xml</filename> configuration files, a tcp port
	and its attributes is defined by an element
	called <emphasis>Connector</emphasis>.  In the following subsections,
	we edit each of these files to specify either one non-SSL connector
	or one SSL connector.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Non-SSL Connectors</title>
	<para>
	  Before editing, the non-SSL connector definition in each of the
	  <filename>server.xml</filename> files looks like this:
	  <screen>
&lt;!-- Define a non-SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 8080 --&gt;
&lt;Connector port="8080"
	  maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
	  enableLookups="false" redirectPort="8443" acceptCount="100"
	  debug="0" connectionTimeout="20000" 
	  disableUploadTimeout="true" /&gt;
	  </screen>
	</para>
	<para>
	  The file 
	  <filename>test/conf/server.xml</filename>
	  does not need to be changed.  The default values fit its
	  requirements.  The <filename>server.xml</filename>
	  files for the other three instances need to be changed,
	  however, as indicated in the next several paragraphs.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <filename>prod/conf/server.xml</filename> after editing:
	  <screen>
&lt;!-- Define a non-SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 80 --&gt;
&lt;Connector port="80"
          maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
          enableLookups="false" redirectPort="443" acceptCount="100"
          debug="0" connectionTimeout="20000" 
          disableUploadTimeout="true" /&gt;
	  </screen>
	  Note that the port number in the comment was changed from
	  8080 to 80, and the value of the redirectPort attribute was 
	  changed from 8443 to 443.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <filename>prodssl/conf/server.xml</filename> after editing:
	  <screen>
&lt;!-- Define a non-SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 8080 --&gt;
&lt;!--
&lt;Connector port="80"
          maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
          enableLookups="false" redirectPort="443" acceptCount="100"
          debug="0" connectionTimeout="20000" 
          disableUploadTimeout="true" /&gt;
--&gt;
	  </screen>
	  Note that the entire Connector element has been commented out.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <filename>testssl</filename> after editing:
	  <screen>  
&lt;!-- Define a non-SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 8080 --&gt;
&lt;!--
&lt;Connector port="80"
          maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
          enableLookups="false" redirectPort="443" acceptCount="100"
          debug="0" connectionTimeout="20000" 
          disableUploadTimeout="true" /&gt;
--&gt;
	  </screen>
	  Note here, too, the entire Connector element has been commented out.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>SSL Connectors</title>
	<para>
	  Before editing, the element for defining the SSL connector will
	  look like this in all four <filename>server.xml</filename> files.
	  Note that the Connector element is commented out.  
	</para>
	<para>
	  <screen>
&lt;!-- Define a SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 8443 --&gt;
&lt;!--
&lt;Connector port="8443"
	  maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
	  enableLookups="false" disableUploadTimeout="true"
	  acceptCount="100" debug="0" scheme="https" secure="true"
	  clientAuth="false" sslProtocol="TLS" /&gt;
--&gt;
	  </screen>
	</para>
	<para>
	  The files <filename>prod/conf/server.xml</filename> and 
	  <filename>test/conf/server.xml</filename> do not have to be changed,
	  because they should not have SSL connectors, hence the fact that the
	  SSL Connector element is commented out by default fits their 
	  requirements.
	  The remaining two <filename>server.xml</filename> files need to be edited
	  as shown in the following paragraphs.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <filename>prodssl/conf/server.xml</filename> after editing:
	  <screen>
&lt;!-- Define a SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 443 --&gt;

&lt;Connector port="443"
	  maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
	  enableLookups="false" disableUploadTimeout="true"
	  acceptCount="100" debug="0" scheme="https" secure="true"
          keystoreFile="/root/.keystore" keystorePass="2bon2btit?"
	  clientAuth="false" sslProtocol="TLS" /&gt;
	  </screen>
	  Note that the comment brackets have been removed, and the port number
	  has been changed from 8443 to 443 in both the introductory comment
	  and as the value of the <emphasis>port</emphasis> attribute.
          Not also that new two entries: 
          <literal>keystore="/root/.keystore" keyPass="2bon2btit?"</literal>.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <filename>testssl/conf/server.xml</filename> after editing:
	  <screen>
&lt;!-- Define a SSL Coyote HTTP/1.1 Connector on port 8443 --&gt;

&lt;Connector port="8443"
	  maxThreads="150" minSpareThreads="25" maxSpareThreads="75"
	  enableLookups="false" disableUploadTimeout="true"
	  acceptCount="100" debug="0" scheme="https" secure="true"
          keystore="/root/.keystore" keyPass="2bon2btit?"
	  clientAuth="false" sslProtocol="TLS" /&gt;
	  </screen>
	  Note that only the comment brackets have been removed.
          Note also that new two entries: 
          <literal>keystore="/root/.keystore" keyPass="2bon2btit?"</literal>.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Disabling the Apache Connector for All Instances</title>
      <para>
	For all four instances, we will comment out the
	element in <filename>server.xml</filename> which defines a connector
	between tomcat and apache, because we are using tomcat as a complete
	stand-alone server that does not depend on apache.
      </para>
      <para>
	Before editing, all four files files, 
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <filename>prod/conf/server.xml</filename>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <filename>test/conf/server.xml</filename>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <filename>prodssl/conf/server.xml</filename>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <filename>testssl/conf/server.xml</filename>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	will look like this:
	<screen>
&lt;!-- Define a Coyote/JK2 AJP 1.3 Connector on port 8009 --&gt;
&lt;Connector port="8009"
	  enableLookups="false" redirectPort="8443" debug="0"
	  protocol="AJP/1.3" /&gt;
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Afterward, all four should look like this:
	<screen>
&lt;!-- Define a Coyote/JK2 AJP 1.3 Connector on port 8009 --&gt;
&lt;!--
&lt;Connector port="8009"
	  enableLookups="false" redirectPort="8443" debug="0"
	  protocol="AJP/1.3" /&gt;
--&gt;
	</screen>
Note that the Connector element has been commented out.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Setting the Instances to Run Automatically</title>
    <para>
      Tomcat should be run automatically from the <command>init</command> process
      whenever the system boots, and be capable of being stopped or restarted manually from
      the command line by the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user, just like other
      system services.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the <filename>r2</filename> CVS repository, in the directory
      <filename>r2/admin/tomcatd</filename>, there are four shell scripts, called
      <command>tomprod</command>,
      <command>tomtest</command>,
      <command>tomprodssl</command>, and
      <command>tomtestssl</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>tomprod</command> looks like this
      <screen>
#!/bin/bash
#
# Init file for production tomcat
#
# chkconfig: 2345 63 37
# description: tomcat server for port 80
#
 
JAVA_HOME=/usr/java/j2sdk1.4.2_03
CATALINA_HOME=/usr/local/tomcat/jakarta-tomcat-5.0.18
CATALINA_BASE=$CATALINA_HOME/../instance/prod
export JAVA_HOME CATALINA_HOME CATALINA_BASE
 
exec $CATALINA_HOME/bin/catalina.sh $*
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Note the line
      <screen>
# chkconfig: 2345 63 37
      </screen>
      It contains values for the <command>/sbin/chkconfig</command>
      utility, which manages the configuration of services in the 
      Linux operating system and in many Unix operating systems, so
      that they are started up and shutdown automatically when the 
      system enters or leaves the appropriate run levels and in
      the correct order.  The line above says that 
      <command>tomprod</command> should be started whenever
      the system enters any of the run levels 2, 3, 4, or 5, and
      that compared to other services, its priority for 
      starting is 63.  It also says that upon leaving any of the given
      run levels, the instance should be stopped with priority 37.
    </para>
    <para>
      The other three scripts differ from the one above only in
      the start priority.  The starting order of the four
      instances are the following:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    63: tomprod
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    64: tomtest
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    65: tomprodssl
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    66: tomtestssl
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Whenever the system reboots, the four instances are started
      in the above order.  If you use the command pipeline
      <command>ps -ef | grep tom</command> to show their run 
      status, you will see them in the order that they were
      started.  This can be useful if, for some reason, the
      <command>kill</command> command has to be used on one of them.
    </para>
    <para>
      To install the four scripts, they must be copied from the
      CVS repository to the directory
      <filename>/etc/rc.d/init.d</filename> and then added
      to the system initialization structures with the help of
      <command>/sbin/chkconfig</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <screen>
cd /tmp
cvs checkout r2
cvs update -dP
cd r2/admin/tomcatd
chmod +x tom*
su
cp tom* /etc/rc.d/init.d
/sbin/chkconfig --add tomprod
/sbin/chkconfig --add tomtest
/sbin/chkconfig --add tomprodssl
/sbin/chkconfig --add tomtestssl
cd /tmp
rm -rf r2
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Setting Authentication Certificates</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Installing for The First Time</title>
      <para>
      If you have not obtained the certificates that tomcat will need for
      https connections, get them by following the instructions in the
      <ulink url="../authentication/authentication.html">
	Authentication and Encryption Howto
      </ulink>.
      If you obtained the certificates on a workstation rather than on the
      web server, transfer a copy of the <filename>cert</filename> directory
      from the ~root directory on the workstation to the ~root directory
      on the server.  To install the the certificates, do the following:
      <screen>
su
cd cert
$JAVA_HOME/bin/keytool -import -alias root -keystore keystore -trustcacerts -file uw_root_cert.pem
$JAVA_HOME/bin/keytool -import -alias tomcat -keystore keystore -trustcacerts -file spk_cert.pem
      </screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Renewal</title>
      <para>
      You are going to request a new SPK certificate from C&amp; and
      replace the old entry in <filename>/root/.keystore</filename>.
      You do not need to do anything about the UW root certificate.
      </para>
      <para>
      First, generate a certificate request from the existing 
      private/public key pair as following:
      <screen>
su -
cd cert
$JAVA_HOME/bin/keytool -certreq -alias tomcat -keyalg RSA -file certreq.csr
      </screen>
      A certificate request, <filename>certreq.csr</filename>,
      is generated using the existing key pair in <filename>/root/.keystore</filename>,
      which is the default location that keytool looks for,
      in <filename>cert</filename> directory. WARNING! It is very & very 
      important to have the key pair and the requested certificate matched!
      </para> 
      <para>
      Submit the request to C&amp;C, following the procedures described in 
      <ulink url="file://192.168.2.2:8080/soft/howto/authentication/authentication.html#AEN77">
      Request a Signed Certificate</ulink> and 
      <ulink url="http://192.168.2.2:8080/soft/howto/rhel3/authentication/authentication.html#AEN81">
      Retrieve your Certificate</ulink>.  Once you retrieved the SPK certifiate, 
      do the following to replace the old certificate entry registered in 
      <filename>/root/.keystore</filename>.
      <screen>
$JAVA_HOME/bin/keytool -delete -alias tomcat
$JAVA_HOME/bin/keytool -import -alias tomcat -trustcacerts -file spk_cert.pem
      </screen>
      The second command, i.e. import, will issue a message saying
      the certifiate you imported was determined as a reply to the 
      certificate request you generated earlier.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Deploying the Spk Web Applications</title>
    <para>
      On your development workstation, do the following process in the directory that
      contains your working copy of the <filename>r2</filename> CVS repository.
      <screen>
cd r2/src/apps/spk/webapps
deploy info prod
deploy info test
deploy user prod
deploy user test
cd ROOT
jar cvf ROOT.jar *
scp ROOT.jar 192.168.2.2:/usr/local/tomcat/instance/prod/webapps
scp ROOT.jar 192.168.2.2:/usr/local/tomcat/instance/test/webapps
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Now you should be ready to start tomcat manually, and to verify that 
      the installation is working.
    </para>
    <para>
      <screen>
su
/etc/rc.d/init.d/tomprod start
/etc/rc.d/init.d/tomtest start
/etc/rc.d/init.d/tomprodssl start
/etc/rc.d/init.d/tomtestssl start
      </screen>
      should get all four instances of tomcat running. You can check that 
      that they are running by using the <command>ps -ef | grep tom</command> command
      pipeline.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once the four instances are running, you can test that the web applications
      are accessible from the web.  If you are outside the firewall, try the URL
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://spk.rfpk.washington.edu/info/">
	https://spk.rfpk.washington.edu/info/
      </ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://spk.rfpk.washington.edu:8443/info/">
	https://spk.rfpk.washington.edu:8443/info/
      </ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      to access <emphasis>info</emphasis> application running in the production
      and the test SSL instances, respectively.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you are behind the firewall, the corresponding URLs are
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://192.168.2.2/info/">
	https://192.168.2.2/info/
      </ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://192.168.2.2:8443/info/">
	https://192.168.2.2:8443/info/
      </ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      To access the <emphasis>user</emphasis> web application,
      click the <guimenuitem>MySpk</guimenuitem> link on any
      of the pages of the <emphasis>info</emphasis> application.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <emphasis>ROOT</emphasis> application, which does nothing
      more than redirect non-SSL requests to the associated SSL
      instance, can only be tested from outside of the firewall.
      The URLs
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu">
	http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu
      </ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu:8080">
	http://spk.rfpk.washington.edu:8080
      </ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
      access the production and test instances respectively.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Stopping and Starting</title>
    <para>
      Tomcat is a daemon. It will run until the <emphasis>root</emphasis>
      user tells it to stop, or until the computer is rebooted.
    </para>
    <para>
      To tell, for example, the test SSL tomcat to stop (as root):
      <screen>
/etc/rc.d/init.d/tomtestssl stop
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Before you try to restart an instance that you have commanded to stop,
      be sure that it has actually terminated by using the piped command
      <command>ps -ef | grep tom</command> and counting entries. Sometimes
      it can take a while for an instance to clean up everything that
      it needs to before quitting.  If it has not died after 
      several minutes, you can use the
      <command>kill -9 pid</command> command, where <emphasis>pid</emphasis>
      is the process id provided by <command>ps</command>. Because
      instances are started at boot time in the order
      <command>prod</command>,
      <command>test</command>,
      <command>prodssl</command>,
      <command>testssl</command>, 
      and hence are assigned monotonically increasing pids, it should 
      ordinarily be possible to decide which process to kill.  If an instance
      has already been stopped and restarted, however, it will have a pid
      greater than any of the processes that have been running since
      boot time. Whenever you restart an instance, it is a good idea to
      write down its pid, in order not to be confused later on.  In practice,
      <command>testssl</command> is the most likely instance to need
      restarting, and in that case there will not be a problem, because
      of the four instances, <command>testssl</command> has the greatest
      pid after boot.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  xml DOCTYPE DocBook uw HOWTO articleinfo revhistory Spk MDA
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  revnumber authorinitials revremark http https servlets su mv
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  servlet whitechuck scp mkdir jakarta cd xvzf orderedlist cp
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  listitem conf webapps itemizedlist webadmin chown chmod rw
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  lt SSL maxThreads minSpareThreads maxSpareThreads clientAuth
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  enableLookups redirectPort acceptCount connectionTimeout TLS
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  disableUploadTimeout  sslProtocol AFter url JSP tcp  RFPK dP
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  keystoreFile ulink Howto keystorePass JK AJP init chkconfig
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  tomtest keystore trustcacerts pem spk ps ef lowerroman CVS
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  internet linkend prodssl testssl tomprod tomprodssl tmp cvs
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  tomtestssl rf cvf guimenuitem MySpk pid pids
 -->
