<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>Downloading and Burning ISOs</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	A reliable method for downloading ISO images and burning them
	onto CD-R is presented.
      </para>
      <para>
	The information in this document is targeted primarily toward
	the RFPK Software Team and associates and is specific to the
	computer systems and network installed in the RFPK Laboratory
	of the &dept; of the &uw;.  RFPK is the Resource for
	Population Kinetics.  Its work is supported, in part, by grant
	P41 EB-001975 of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) of
	the U.S.  Department of Health and Human Services.
      </para>
      <para>
	<link linkend="copyright">Copyright</link> (c) 2004, by the &uw;.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>July 4, 1776</date>
	<authorinitials></authorinitials>
	<revremark></revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The RedHat Linux operating software and many other software products
      are made available for download as a set of ISO images.  Each
      image, typically presented as a file whose name ends with the
      suffix <filename>.iso</filename>, represents the contents of a 
      CDROM.  If the installation set for the product consists of four
      CDROMs, you need to download four ISO image files and then burn
      each of them onto CD-R.  Because these files are so large, an 
      efficient process is required.  Because the reliability of the 
      software to be installed from these ISOs is of critical importance,
      there must be a way to test that the process of downloaded and
      burning was error-free.  This document presents a reliable method
      for creating installation CDROMs from downloaded ISOs.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Downloading</title>
    <para>
      The files are first downloaded from a web site or from an ftp server.
      The ftp protocol is normally used, although other protocols, including
      html, are often available and can do the job.  
    </para>
    <para>
      At the download site, you need to find two pieces of information:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The file or files to be downloaded.  The file name typically
	    indicates the name of the product and the version, and the
	    suffix is normally <filename>.iso</filename>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    An MD5 checksum for each file.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Proceed to download the file or files.  After the download is complete,
      use <emphasis>md5sum</emphasis> to compute the MD5 checksum for each
      file you have received.  For example, if a file that was downloaded 
      was called <filename>KNOPPIX_V3.6-2004-08-16-EN.iso</filename>,
      you would compute the checksum as follows:
      <screen>
md5sum KNOPPIX_V3.6-2004-08-16-EN.iso
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      In this example based on Knoppix, a version of Linux contained on a single
      bootable CDROM, the MD5 checksum at the 
      download site is actually in a file called
      <filename>KNOPPIX_V3.6-2004-08-16-EN.iso.md5</filename>, which
      can be easily downloaded and checked against the value computed
      by <emphasis>md5sum</emphasis>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Burning</title>
    <para>
      Once you have downloaded your ISOs and have verified their integrity using
      <emphasis>md5sum</emphasis>, you are ready to burn CDROMs.  In the following
      example, we burn the single Knoppix CDROM:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Place a blank CDR in your CD burner.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If a GUI cd burning program starts automatically, close the window.
	    We will use <emphasis>cdrecord</emphasis> from the command line.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Open a shell window and use <command>su</command> to become the root
	    user.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Enter the following command at the commandline prompt:
	    <screen>
cdrecord -v dev=0,0,0 speed=40 driveropts=burnfree -dao -eject /opt/incoming/KNOPPIX_V3.6-2004-08-16-EN.iso
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Note that the device triplet, <emphasis>0,0,0</emphasis> may not be correct for your
	    system.  Determine the correct values by running the command
	    <command>cdrecord --scanbus</command>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Note that the following options are essential:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>driveropts=burnfree</emphasis> enables buffer underflow protection
		  in the drive.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>-dao</emphasis>, or "disk at once", causes the entire disk
		  to be written. Without this, subsequent running of <emphasis>md5sum</emphasis>
		  on the device may hang.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You will, of course, change the filename at the end of the command to
	    whatever is appropriate for the software you have downloaded.
	    You may also want to change the speed to accord with the lesser of the 
	    speed of your cd burner and the speed capability of your blank CDR.  
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If all goes well, your CDROM will be written without any error detected 
	    by <emphasis>cdrecord</emphasis> and the disk will eject.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Without removing the CDROM you have just burned, close the drive.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Compute the MD5 checksum for the CDROM:
	    <screen>
md5sum /dev/cdrom
	    </screen>
	    This may take five minutes or more, because the entire CDROM must be
	    read.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The value computed must be identical to that obtained previously from
	    the ISO and to that published on the download site.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Unmount the CDROM. If the checksum was correct, the CDROM is 
	    ready to use.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title id="copyright">Copyright Notice</title>
    <para>
      Copyright (c) 2004,  by the University of Washington.
      This material may be distributed only subject to the terms and conditions 
      set forth in the Open Publication License, V1.0 or later
      (the latest version is presently available
      <ulink url="http://www.opencontent.org/openpub/">here</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>


<!--  LocalWords:  xml DOCTYPE DocBook uw articleinfo SPK RFPK RFPK's linkend
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  ulink url CDROMs revhistory revnumber authorinitials RedHat
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  revremark iso CDROM ISOs html orderedlist listitem md CDR cd
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  Knoppix bootable cdrecord su commandline dev driveropts dao
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  burnfree scanbus itemizedlist
 -->
