<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
  <!ENTITY whitechuck '<systemitem class="systemname">whitechuck</systemitem>'>
]>
<article><title>Operating System Version Migration</title>
 <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>January 4, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  <abstract>
      <para>
	Instructions and advice for migrating from RedHat Linux
	version 8.0 to RedHat Enterprise Linux Version 3 are given.
      </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      RedHat Enterprise Linux, Version 3 (RHEL3), is closely related to 
      RedHat Linux 8.0 (RH8), but the differences are great enough
      that a simple update is not possible.  In the future, when
      we go from one version of RHEL to the next, an update function
      that preserves data and applications while upgrading
      the operating system will be available.  No such update function is 
      offered for the migration from RH8 to RHEL3.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Even when such an update function is available, it is dangerous
      to use.  If the update process fails after having made
      irreversible changes to a hard disk, the recovery process
      is likely to be very difficult and only partially successful.
    </para>
    <para>
      Our strategy to reduce risk and to simplify the migration 
      process is to utilize two hard disks.  One disk
      contains the current operating system and all of the
      software and data that needs to be preserved. During the
      migration it will be untouched.  After the migration, it
      will be placed on-line in a read-only state, so that its
      contents will be fully accessible.  The other disk 
      contains nothing that requires preservation. Its contents
      will be completely wiped out.  It is the disk on which
      the new version will be installed.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is always some risk that the first disk will not be
      readable after the new system is installed. In such a case
      we have to fall back onto the backups which were copied to
      the whitechuck server. Part of the preparation described
      in the next section is concerned with making sure that
      these backups would be available if needed.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Preparation</title>
    <para>
      It is imperative that we collect information about the
      current system and store it in forms that will not
      be over-written when the new version is installed.
      Some of the data has already been provided by the automatic nightly
      backups to whitechuck.  We must verify that these backups
      are usable. Some additional data not
      included in the nightly backups must be copied to
      whitechuck.  Finally, the contents of some key configuration
      files must be printed out.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Get a Hard Copy of this Document</title>
      <para>
	If you have not already done so, print out a copy of this document
	from its <filename>.pdf</filename> file.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Verify the Backup of your Home Directory</title>
      <para>
	Each weekday night, your system should be copying your
	home directory to &whitechuck;. You should verify that
	this is working correctly.  Here is one way to do that:
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In a terminal window, go to the directory on
	      &whitechuck; which contains your backup copies:
	      <screen>
ssh whitechuck
cd backup
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If you run <command>ls -l</command>, you should see a
	      list of directory names, each starting with the date
	      on which the backup was taken. Go 
	      <command>cd</command> to the most recent backup, and
	      then take a directory listing:
	      <screen>
cd <emphasis>most-recent-backup</emphasis>
ls -lR $USER > /tmp/backup_listing
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open a terminal window on your workstation, and
	      make a similar directory listing there, retrieve the 
	      listing made on &whitechuck;, and use <command>diff</command>
	      to compare the two:
	      <screen>
cd ..
ls -lR $USER > /tmp/current_listing
cd /tmp
scp whitechuck:/tmp/backup_listing .
diff current_listing backup_listing
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the backup is recent, the output from the 
	      <command>diff</command> command should be short. Check 
	      into any differences that come as a surprise.  At the
	      end of this process, you must be confident that your
	      backup is good.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Make a Copy of <filename>/etc</filename></title>
      <para>
	Most of the configuration files on your workstation reside in the
	<filename>/etc</filename> directory.  If certain functions 
	no longer work after the migration, it will be useful to be
	able to consult previous versions of the configuration files.
	From a terminal window, here is a convenient way to make
	a copy:
	<screen>
su -
cd /
tar cvzf /tmp/etc.tgz etc
chown $USER /tmp/etc.tgz
exit
scp /tmp/etc.tgz whitechuck:
	</screen>
	Upon completing the command sequence listed above,
	a new tar ball named <filename>etc.tgz</filename> should 
	appear in your home directory on &whitechuck;.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Plan the Migration of Non-RPM Packages</title>
      <para>
	The overwhelming majority of software packages on your workstation
	were installed by the Redhat Package Manager (RPM).  When
	you install RHEL, later versions of these packages will be
	installed automatically.  You may, however, have several 
	packages that were not installed by RPM.  These are most
	likely located in <filename>/usr/local</filename>, although
	they may be elsewhere.  Only you know what these packages
	are.
      </para>
      <para>
	There are two basic ways to handle the migration of
	your non-RPM packages:
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Reinstall them from scratch.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Similar to the way that you placed a copy of 
	      <filename>/etc</filename> on &whitechuck;
	      place a copy of the tar ball for each package
	      somewhere safe, so that you can copy it back 
	      and expand it after the migration.  Note, however,
	      that this might not work, because the package 
	      might depend in some way on RedHat 8.0 that is 
	      not compatible with RHEL.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	Just to be on the safe side, it might be best to make a 
	copy of any non-RPM package that you are really depending
	on, even though your intention is to reinstall from scratch.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Print Out Configuration Files and Reports</title>
      <para>
	We need to list some key network configuration files
	and reports describing the layout of the filesystem:
	<screen>
pr /etc/resolv.conf | lpr
pr /etc/hosts | lpr
pr /etc/sysconfig/network | lpr
pr /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-eth0 | lpr
pr /etc/fstab | lpr
df | lpr
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Commit your CVS Changes</title>
      <para>
	Be sure to commit any changes that you have made to 
	your CVS work space.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Install RHEL from Cdrom</title>
    <para>
      There are five RHEL3 installation cdroms.  Of these, you will 
      probably only need the first three.  Important steps in the
      installation process are listed below.  Not all interactions
      with the installation GUI are covered, because many items
      are either obvious or you have simply to agree with something
      that the software has already figured out.  When in doubt,
      accept the value that the software suggests.
    </para>
    <para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Automatic Partitioning.  Your machine contains two hard 
	    drives. We <emphasis>do not</emphasis> want to remove
	    anything on the drive that you are currently using
	    for linux.  Instead, RHEL will be installed on the drive
	    that currently contains Windows.  Be certain that you 
	    select the Windows drive for RHEL installation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Network Configuration. In the 
	    <guimenu>hostname</guimenu>
	    section of this screen, select the
	    <guibutton>manually</guibutton> radio button,
	    then type in your complete Internet host name.  It will
	    be a name of the form
	    <filename>name.rfpk.washington.edu</filename>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Firewall. We definitely want the firewall to be enabled.
	    Check only the <guimenuitem>SSH</guimenuitem> box
	    in the list of services to allow through the firewall.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Time Zone.  Check the 
	    <guimenuitem>System Clock Uses UTC</guimenuitem> box, and
	    a Pacific Timezone city, such as 
	    <guimenuitem>America/Los_Angeles</guimenuitem>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Root Password. You can use the same root password that you
	    are using now. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Package Installation Defaults. Check the 
	    <guimenuitem>Customize ...</guimenuitem> box.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Package Group Selection.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>In addition to the boxes already check-marked by default</emphasis>
	    select the following package groups:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Engineering and Scientific.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Authoring and Publishing.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Web Server.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  MySQL Database.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  KDE Software Development.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Legacy Software Development.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  System Tools.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      If all goes well, you should reach the end of the installation
      process.  Press the <guibutton>Exit</guibutton> button, and
      the machine will boot up on RHEL3. 
    </para>
    <para>
      Once you have booted, a post-configuration GUI starts 
      automatically.  Here are some additional steps:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Date and Time.  Check the
	    <guimenuitem>Enable Network Time Protocol</guimenuitem>
	    box and select either of the servers listed in the
	    <guimenuitem>Server</guimenuitem> box.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    User account.  Enter the same username and password that
	    you were using for your ordinary user login before the
	    migration.  <emphasis>You do not need to do
	    a network login.</emphasis>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    At this point, the installation is complete.  Reboot
	    your system, to ensure that any updates will go
	    into effect.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Start Mozilla to Access this Document</title>
    <para>
      Start Mozilla.  A RedHat registration page will appear.  
      Ignore it, and type the following URL into the field
      at the top of the page:
      <screen>
whitechuck.rfpk.washington.edu/soft/index.html
      </screen>
      This should bring up the Software Team web page, from 
      which you can bring up a copy of this document..  In the
      steps that follow, having a copy on the screen will facilitate
      entering commands into shell windows, because you can
      cut and paste.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Make Old Disk Accessible</title>
    <para>
      Your old disk, with your RH8 installation, should now be made 
      accessible.  We mount the partitions of the old disk on
      a directory called <filename>/old</filename> which we will
      create on the new disk.
    </para>
    <para>
      List all the disk partitions known to RHEL:
      <screen>
su -
fdisk -l
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      You will get a list of the partitions of both your disks. 
      Compare this with the output of the
      <command>df</command> that you printed before the 
      migration.  This latter list shows what mount points
      the partitions had before migration.
    </para>
    <para>
      By comparing the two lists, determine whether the disk
      device changed. This might have happened if you 
      changed the physical connections of your hard drives
      as might occur, for example, if you added a second
      drive.  
    </para>
    <para>
      As root,
      create an empty directory 
      on which the old partitions will be mounted:
      <screen>
mkdir /old
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Make a backup copy of <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>:
      <screen>
cd /etc
cp fstab fstab.bak
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      With <command>emacs</command>, edit <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>,
      adding one line for each of the old partitions that you want
      to mount.
    </para>
    <para>
      For example, assume that a comparison of the old 
      <command>df</command> listing with the current output of
      <command>fdisk -l</command> shows that the contents of
      the current <filename>/dev/hdb1</filename> was mounted previously
      on <filename>/</filename>. In this case you would add the 
      following line:
      <screen>
/dev/hdb1      /old           ext3    ro,suid,dev,exec,auto,nouser,async  1 2
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      With the above definition, paths relative to 
      <filename>/</filename> on the old system will now be
      relative to <filename>/old</filename> on the new one.
      For example, the old <filename>/home</filename> is
      now <filename>/old/home</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Further suppose that the contents of the current
      <filename>/dev/hdb3</filename> used to be mounted on
      <filename>/home</filename>.  We add the following line to
      <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>:
      <screen>
/dev/hdb3      /old/home      ext3    ro,suid,dev,exec,auto,nouser,async  1 2
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Suppose that the contents of the current
      <filename>/dev/hdb5</filename> was mounted previously on
      <filename>/usr</filename>.  We add this line:
      <screen>
/dev/hdb5      /old/usr       ext3    ro,suid,dev,exec,auto,nouser,async  1 2
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Continue until all of the "Linux" file systems (not including the "Linux swap"
      file system) shown on the <command>fdisk -l</command> listing have been
      accounted for with lines added to <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>.
      You may need fewer than three lines.  You may need more.  It all
      depends on how many ordinary linux filesystem partitions your old
      system had.
    </para>
    <para>
      Save <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>, then reboot your system.
      When you now do <command>df</command>, you should see that the
      old partitions are mounted.
    </para>
  </sect1>
<sect1>
    <title>Restore Your Home Directory</title>
    <para>
      After establishing access to your old home directory,
      you are ready to restore most
      of its contents.  To do this, we will use the
      <command>rsync</command> command, which gives us a convenient
      means of copying a directory tree while excluding a few
      things we do not want copied.  In particular, we do not
      want to overwrite the gnome, rhn, nautilus and metacity
      settings that have just been set up by the RHEL installation.
    </para>
    <para>
      From a terminal window:
      <screen>
cd
H=/old/home/$USER
export H
su
rsync -a --exclude '.g*' --exclude '.rhn*' --exclude '.nautilus*' --exclude '.metacity*' $H/* $H/.* .
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      To complete this process, go to the 
      <guimenu>Main</guimenu> menu and select
      <guimenuitem>Log Out</guimenuitem>.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, log in again.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Restore Static IP</title>
    <para>
      After the migration, RHEL communicated with a DHCP server in
      the UW network to get information to set up Internet access.
      This works fine, but at this point your machine is not
      accessible by name from the outside, because the IP that
      DHCP assigns can change every time you restart your network
      interface.  For the time being, at least, the Software Team
      workstations are accessible by host name from the Internet,
      because they have had static IP addresses assigned.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Do the following to restore your static IP address
      (note that <command>su</command> is not followed by the
      - option symbol):
      <screen>
su 
cd /etc/sysconfig/network-scripts
cp ifcfg-eth0 ifcfg-eth0.bak
cp /old/etc/sysconfig/network-scripts/ifcfg-eth0 .
/etc/rc.d/init.d/network restart
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Register with the RedHat Network</title>
    <para>
      Now that you have restored your static IP address, you
      can register with RedHat Network. RFPK purchases a set
      of annual subscriptions that entitle our RHEL machines
      to receive automatic updates, via the
      <command>up2date</command> program.  In this section,
      you register your machine with RedHat so that this
      function is enabled.
    </para>
    <para>
      Notice the small red-colored circle at the lower right-hand
      corner of the screen, just to the left of the date and
      time.  Double click this to start <command>up2date</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Follow the dialog.  At some point you will be asked to 
      register with RedHat Network and presented with a 
      window that allows you to either 
      <guimenuitem>Create a New Account</guimenuitem> or
      <guimenuitem>Use Existing Account</guimenuitem>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Click the <guimenuitem>Use Existing Account</guimenuitem>
      radio button and supply this information:
      <screen>
	Username:        alanwesthagen
	Password:        (get this from the Software Team manager)
	Email address:   afw@u.washington.edu
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      This should link you up to use one of the
      RedHat Network Management Entitlements that RFPK has purchased.
      The <command>up2date</command> wizard will start
      automatically.  Allow it to install any updates
      to RHEL Version 3 that have been created since the
      cdroms were made, including updates to the kernel.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Set Up Printers</title>
    <para>
      There are two Hewlett Packard laser printers located in the lab:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    HP LaserJet 4200 dtn, located near the front door to the lab.
	    This printer has its own interface to the network, and its
	    own domain name, which is <emphasis>arunta</emphasis>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    HP LaserJet 5000 dtn, locate near the back door to the lab.
	    At present, this printer's network interface is broken.
	    The firewall on whitechuck prevents us from accessing
	    this  printer, at the present time.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring lj4200</title>
      <para>
	To configure access to the LaserJet 4200:
	Bring up the <guimenuitem>Printer Configuration</guimenuitem> window:
	<screen>
	  <guimenu>Main</guimenu> => <guimenu>System Settings</guimenu> => <guimenuitem>Printing</guimenuitem>
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Press the <guibutton>New</guibutton> button to bring up the
	<guimenuitem>Add a new print queue</guimenuitem> window.
	Provide this "wizard" with the following answers:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guilabel>Name</guilabel>: lj4200
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guilabel>Short description</guilabel>: HP LaserJet 4200 near front door
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guimenu>Select a queue type</guimenu>: Networked JetDirect
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guilabel>Printer</guilabel>: arunta
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <guilabel>Select the printer manufacturer and model</guilabel>: PostScript Printer
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	Let the wizard <guibutton>apply</guibutton> this definition and 
	print a test page.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring lj5000</title>
      <para>
	As explained above, the firewall on whitechuck inhibits
	us from accessing this printer until the JetDirect
	interface is repaired.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Restore Password-Free SSH Connections</title>
    <para>
      If you have previously followed the instructions in the
      <emphasis>SSH Configuration Howto</emphasis> to enable
      your workstation to create secure connections to remote
      hosts without requiring a password except when your
      desktop manager starts up, you will want to follow the
      steps in this section.
    </para>
    <para>
      Configure the Gnome desktop manager.
      <screen format="linespecific">
<guimenu moreinfo="none">Main</guimenu> => <guimenu moreinfo="none">Preferences</guimenu> => <guimenu moreinfo="none">More Preferences</guimenu> => <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Sessions</guimenuitem> => left-click
      </screen>
      This will open the <interface moreinfo="none">Sessions</interface>
      window.  Press the 
      <guibutton moreinfo="none">Startup Programs</guibutton> button
      followed by
      the <guibutton moreinfo="none">Add</guibutton> button.  Then
      set the following variables:
      <screen format="linespecific">
	Startup Command: /usr/bin/ssh-add
	Priority: 70
      </screen>
      Close the window by pressing the
      <guibutton moreinfo="none">OK</guibutton> button.
    </para>
    <para>
      To complete this process, go to the 
      <guimenu>Main</guimenu> menu and select
      <guimenuitem>Log Out</guimenuitem>.  
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, log in again.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Update CVS</title>
    <para>
      During the migration, other developers may have committed
      changes to the cvs repository.  This would be a good time
      to update your cvs work space.
    </para>
    <para>
      Assume that R2 contains the path of the root of your workspace:
      <screen>
cd $R2
cvs update -dP
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Restore Clock Synchronization</title>
    <para>
      If your workstation was previously configured to use the
      network time protocol to automatically synchronize its
      internal clock that of whitechuck,
      you can easily restore this function by executing the
      following commands from a shell window.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note: <command>su</command> is not followed by the 
      - option symbol.
      <screen>
su
cd /etc
mv ntp.conf ntp.conf.bak
mv ntp/step-tickers ntp/step-tickers.bak
cp /old/etc/ntp.conf .
cp /old/etc/ntp/step-tickers ntp 
/etc/rc.d/init.d/ntpd restart
/sbin/chkconfig --level 2345 ntpd on
      </screen>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Restore the Backup Function</title>
    <para>
      Perform the following menu sequence:
	<screen format="linespecific">
<guimenu moreinfo="none">Main</guimenu> => <guimenu moreinfo="none">Preferences</guimenu> => <guimenu moreinfo="none">More Preferences</guimenu> => <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Sessions</guimenuitem> => left-click
	</screen>
	This will open the <interface moreinfo="none">Sessions</interface>
	window.  Press the 
	<guibutton moreinfo="none">Startup Programs</guibutton> button
	followed by
	the <guibutton moreinfo="none">Add</guibutton> button.  Then
	set the following variables:
	<screen format="linespecific">
Startup Command: /home/<emphasis>username</emphasis>/bin/shell/get-agent-data
Priority: 75
	</screen>
      where <emphasis>username</emphasis> is your username.
      Close the window by pressing the
      <guibutton moreinfo="none">OK</guibutton> button.
    </para>
    <para>
      As an ordinary user, from a terminal window, execute the following
      command:
      <screen>
crontab -e
      </screen>
      and an <command>emacs</command> window should appear, displaying
      the <filename>crontab</filename> file, ready for editing
      (the file might be empty at this point).
    </para>
    <para>
      Add the following line:
      <screen>
30 2 * * 2-6 ~/bin/shell/backup-home-full
      </screen>
Close the file, and your home directory will be backed up to
whitechuck 2:30 AM, each morning that follows a work day.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Reinstall Acrobat Reader</title>
    <para>
      If your prefer the Adobe Acrobat Reader to the default
      reader provided with RHEL, you will need to reinstall 
      <command>acroread.</command>  This is easily accomplished by
      following the steps in the
      <ulink url="../acroread/acroread.html">
	Acrobat Reader Installation
      </ulink> howto.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Install Dia</title>
    <para>
      Dia, the Gnu Office diagramming tool, is not included in the
      RHEL distribution.  It can be easily installed, following the
      instructions in the 
      <ulink url="../authoring/authoring.html">
	<emphasis>Authoring RFPK Software Documents</emphasis>
      </ulink>
      howto, in the <emphasis>Installing Dia</emphasis> sub-section.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  xml DOCTYPE DocBook uw whitechuck systemitem systemname afw
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  articleinfo revhistory revnumber authorinitials revremark cd
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  RedHat Redhat RHEL orderedlist listitem lR tmp scp su cvzf
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  chown tgz lpr Cdrom mkdir lt ln RHN RFPK alanwesthagen cp mv
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  linkend xvzf pre rsync rhn guimenu guimenuitem Howto ntp pdf
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  linespecific moreinfo guibutton conf ntpd username CVS linux
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  cdroms hostname UTC itemizedlist MySQL Mozilla fdisk df bak
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  fstab ro suid dev nouser async usr filesystem metacity IP dP
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  DHCP ifcfg eth cvs crontab acroread ulink url howto
 -->
