<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
     "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
]>
<article><title>An Architectural Overview of SPK</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Alan</firstname>
      <surname>Westhagen</surname>
      <affiliation>
	<jobtitle>Software Architect</jobtitle>
	<jobtitle>RFPK Software Team Leader</jobtitle>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>July 1, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	The System for Population Kinetics (SPK) is software being developed
	by the RFPK Laboratory, in the Bioengineering Department of the 
	University of Washington, under grant <emphasis>P41 EB-001975</emphasis>
	from the National Institutes
	of Health (NIH) of the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.	
	This whitepaper describes its architecture.
    </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>What the Architecture Supports</title>
    <para>
      This section describes the requirements that the SPK architecture
      is designed to satisfy.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Problem to be Solved</title>
      <para>
	To better understand and to predict the operation of biological
	systems, researchers design mathematical models which they 
	believe will closely conform to observations.  The
	equations that comprise these models contain parameters whose
	values must be determined by "fitting" the equations to real-world
	data.  In the biomedical field of population kinetics (PK), a methodology
	known as <emphasis>nonlinear mixed-effects modeling</emphasis>
	has been very successful.  This technique, when properly applied,
	can provide models which
	accurately project the behavior of an entire population from
	a small number of observations collected from a small sample 
	of individuals.  This makes this technology 
	very attractive in medicine and pharmaceutical 
	development, because collecting data from living subjects is a
	difficult, time-consuming, sometimes risky and, inevitably, expensive procedure.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Computational Challenge</title>
      <para>
	From a computational stand-point, the process of developing
	nonlinear mixed-effects models presents some interesting challenges.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Computing the parameters is highly processor intensive. In 
	      developing a model, it may be necessary
	      to perform the computation many times.  On a 
	      very fast workstation, each recalculation of the
	      model can take a week.  On a typical single processor workstation,
	      only one such calculation can be performed at a time.
	      Clearly, it would be desirable to offload the 
	      calculation to a specialized computational engine.
	      Going even further, it would be highly desirable
	      to distribute the calculation over a cluster of
	      processors, for parallel computation.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Although a high performance cluster is the ideal 
	      platform for model computation, it is unacceptable,
	      by itself, as a platform for model design and
	      results analysis.  Model design is a creative 
	      process, and the user needs appropriate tools to 
	      enhance this process.  The preferred platform
	      to support these tools is the same one the user
	      employs for other creative work, such as 
	      writing papers, preparing presentations, 
	      communicating with colleagues, etc.  In nearly
	      every case, this platform will be a personal computer
	      workstation or laptop running the user's preferred
	      operating system, whether Windows, Macintosh ,or Linux.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Internet connectivity is just as important as her
	      workstation or laptop to the creative
	      designer of PK models.
	      While a model's parameters are 
	      being computed, the user will be working on other models
	      or unrelated work, but will need to monitor
	      the progress of her PK jobs as they are processed
	      to completion.  The user should be able, for example,
	      to submit a job
	      for computation at her office, obtain results and
	      resubmit a modified model at an airport en route to a 
	      conference, and receive the completed work upon arrival
	      at her destination.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>SPK is a Web Service</title>
      <para>
	SPK is a service delivered to researchers via the world wide
	web, which enables them to develop, compute and validate PK models quickly and
	efficiently. The service is offered to a designated set of 
	users by an SPK service provider.  At the present time, the
	only SPK service provider is RFPK itself, but in the future,
	many additional service providers,
	located at both academic and commercial research laboratories,
	are envisioned.
      </para>
      <para>
	Although SPK can run on a single machine, its real power can
	only be realized when a high performance computational cluster
	is involved. Computer resources cost money, hence the SPK
	service will not be free. We believe that competition between
	service providers will, however, insure that pricing will 
	be fair.  In part to encourage the establishment of as many
	SPK installations as possible, SPK software will be distributed 
	free-of-charge under an open source license.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title id="mda">The User Perspective</title>
      <para>
	The user's access to SPK is provided by two graphical user interface
	(GUI) programs.  One of these is simply the web browser of the user's
	choice, such as Internet Explorer, Mozilla, or Opera. 
	The other is a component of SPK called the Model
	Design Agent (MDA).
      </para>
      <para>
	The MDA is written in the Java language, so that
	it works under nearly any operating system, including 
	Windows, Linux and Macintosh.  The first time the user 
	accesses an SPK installation with her browser,
	she is lead through the downloading and installation 
	of the MDA and, if not already present,
	the Java runtime environment.  This only takes a few 
	minutes.  At the beginning of subsequent sessions, she
	does not need to download any software unless updated 
	versions are available, in which case, the download and 
	installation occur automatically.
      </para>
      <para>
	The following is an abbreviated list of functions that a 
	user can perform with the assistance of the MDA:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Specify a new model and save it in a central database
	      maintained by the service provider.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Update an existing model to create a new version.
	      The new version does not destroy its predecessor.
	      Instead, all versions are preserved by means of a 
	      revision control system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Import or create a dataset and save it in the central
	      database.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Update a dataset, creating a new version.  Datasets
	      are also maintained by the revision control system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Combine a model, dataset or dataset simulation parameters.
	      initial estimates of model parameters
	      and some additional information to create a job and
	      submit it for transformation into an executable program and
	      subsequent running on the computational engine.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Check the status of all jobs that the user has submitted.
	      At a given moment in time, a job can be
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    In a queue, waiting to be transformed into a C++
		    program by the SPK compiler.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Being processed by the SPK compiler.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    In queue, waiting to be transformed from C++ into
		    executable binary code and then run on the computational
		    engine.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Being processed by the computational engine.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    At end.  Report available.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Provide a simple and convenient presentation of results.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Export results in forms required by other analysis and
	      visualization tools.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Create a new job by cloning a previous job, changing 
	      initial arguments, run parameters, method or dataset.
	      For example,  SPK currently supports several methods of 
	      calculation, including 
	      <emphasis>first order </emphasis>,
	      <emphasis>expected Hessian </emphasis>,
	      <emphasis>Laplace approximation </emphasis> and
	      <emphasis>Monte Carlo likelihood </emphasis>, 
	      which have been listed in order of increasing computational cost.
	      The user might want to start with a quick 
	      computation using the first order method, then
	      follow with one of the more expensive methods,
	      using as initial estimates the first order results.
	      The MDA makes this very convenient for users.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title id="ssp">The Service Provider Perspective</title>
      <para>
	The MDA, described in the section 
	<link linkend="mda">above</link>, is the
	<emphasis>client side</emphasis> of
	SPK.  Everything else is on the 
	<emphasis>server side</emphasis>, which is provided 
	by an <emphasis>SPK service provider</emphasis>.
        A service provider might simply be
	a function within an academic department. It might be an operation
	of a a campus-wide department of academic computing. The
	service provider might be part of the IT department of a commercial
	lab or pharmaceutical company.  It might be a service provided
	by a consulting organization to its clients. 
      </para>
      <para>
	There are, inevitably, costs involved with providing SPK service.
	In some cases, these costs are simply absorbed in departmental
	budgets or research grants.  In other cases, costs will be billed
	back to users. Commercial operations may want to build a profit into the
	fees that they charge. At present, SPK software does not contain
	any functions that directly support billing. Information that could
	provide the basis for billing or charge-back is, however, present in
	the database.
      </para>
      <para>
	SPK does not require any predetermined set of computers.  It
	is, in fact, possible to run the entire system on a single 
	machine.  Other than for demonstration purposes, however,
	using a single machine does not make sense, because this
	brings insufficient computational power to bear. At RFPK,
	the server side consists of two server machines, plus a
	computational cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
	In discussing Internet software, one is just as likely to 
	apply the designation of <emphasis>server</emphasis> to a 
	program as to a machine. For example, the Apache Web Server
	is software, not hardware.  It is common for more than one
	software server to run on a single machine.  It is also common
	for a software server which requires a lot of resources to
	be replicated on multiple machines in order to share the
	load.
      </para>
      <para>
	From a software point of view,
	the server side of SPK consists of an
	application server, computational server, a web server and
	a database server. At RFPK, the web server is a separate 
	machine for security reasons, the application and database
	server share a machine, and the computational server runs on a 
	computational cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
	All SPK server-side software is developed using the GNU software
	development tools to be portable to any
	Linux or Unix environment.  Unlike the client-side MDA,
	the server side cannot
	be run on Windows and Macintosh systems.
      </para>
      <para>
	Installing and operating
	the server side is non-trivial.  In the development of SPK,
	a strategic decision was made to move as much of the inherent
	complexity of the system onto the server side as possible, in 
	order to maximize the convenience to the end user.  The server side
	is no more complex, however, than comparable web-based applications,
	and well within the competence of system administrators typically
	found in university departments or commercial research facilities.
      </para>
      <para>
        SPK is distributed free-of-charge under an open source license.  
	This distribution strategy reduces the risk to service providers,
	because they can modify or continue the development of SPK 
	independent of RFPK, if necessary.  On the other hand, RFPK 
	eagerly encourages collaborative development by all other 
	interested parties.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Software Developer Perspective</title>
      <para>
	RFPK uses the GNU GCC compiler and many related tools to develop
	most of the
	SPK server-side software, and the Standard Edition of Sun Java-2
	for the MDA. The MySQL relational database management system
	is a key component. Programming languages include C, C++,
	Perl, and Java. Source code is managed by the CVS revision control
	system.  All of the computers used in software development at
	RFPK run RedHat Enterprise Linux, version 3.
      </para>
      <para>
	One of the reasons for distributing SPK under an open source license
	is to encourage cooperative development of the software.  Any
	organization or individual has access to the source code and 
	the same open source development tools used by RFPK. A 
	development and test environment can be set up very inexpensively
	on a few PCs.  RFPK is eager to work with any serious co-developers.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Current Status and Future Directions</title>
      <para>
	At the present time (July, 2004), SPK would have to be classed as 
	a <emphasis>beta</emphasis> product.  The only service provider is
	RFPK itself, and the only users are scientists associated with the
	lab.  It will be at least nine months before source code will be well
	enough organized for general release.  The system is being tested
	in end-to-end mode and the initial results look good.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the coming months, these are some of the capabilities that
	will be added:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Support for model functions expressed as differential
	      equations. (At present, only algebraic functions are supported).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Support for parallel computation.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Open source distribution of the software, via the
	      Internet.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Architectural Strategy</title>
    <para>
      The design of SPK is guided by certain architectural 
      principals:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Emphasize user effectiveness.</emphasis>
	    The user's time is very valuable. Don't give the user a product that is
	    hard to install or hard to use. Trade increased complexity
	    on the server side for simplicity on the client side.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Build security into every stage</emphasis>. SPK employs 
	    public key authentication and the
	    secure socket layer (SSL) security for connections across the
	    public Internet, password security and session security for the
	    MDA, and firewall security for the server network.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Incorporate only open source software</emphasis>.  
	    This is, of course, a requirement for open source distribution.  
	    Equally important, however, is the access that this policy affords
	    to a wealth of open source components which can be freely incorporated
	    into SPK without the need to expend resources negotiating 
	    commercial licensing and pricing issues.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Minimize dependencies between major modules</emphasis>.
	    It must be  possible to modify
	    a module with little or no impact on other
	    modules.  In practical terms, this means that all communication
	    between modules must be tightly controlled, fully documented,
	    and narrow-band.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Employ existing technologies whenever possible</emphasis>.
	    Among the technologies employed are the MySQL relational database
	    management system as the channel for all inter-server communication;
	    the Gnu versions of Lex and Yacc for building the SPK compiler;
	    the Xerces XML parser;
	    Sun Java-2 and the Java Runtime Engine;
	    the NetBeans IDE for building the graphical
	    user interface; Java WebStart for rich-client java technology;
	    the secure socket layer (SSL) to encrypt Internet communications;
	    RCS for version control.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Software Architecture</title>
    <para>
      <figure float="1">
	<title>Software Architecture</title>
	<graphic scale="50" fileref="logical.png"/>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title id="central">Centrality of the Database</title>
      <para>
	Architecturally, SPK software is built around a relational database.
	Every significant change in the state of the system is recorded there.
	For instance, a user's models and datasets are stored in the database. An
	implication of this is that the user can employ one workstation at the office,
	another at home and a third on the road without ever having to 
	"synchronize" them.  Because models and datasets are stored
	in a version control format, all versions of a model or dataset,
	from the first to the most recent, are available. 
      </para>
      <para>
	To have SPK compute model parameters, a user <emphasis>submits</emphasis>
	a job. Behind the scenes, the MDA passes a request to the web server
	which, in turn, creates a new row in the <emphasis>job table</emphasis> 
	of the database.  From that point onward, the application server and
	the computational server access the database for all of their inputs and
	outputs concerning that job. Finally, the computational results are
	retrieved from the database by the MDA via the web server.
      </para>
      <para>
	The use of a database as the sole medium of communication between the 
	web server, the application server and the computational server is a
	powerful expression of the concept that inter-module communication paths
	should be very narrow and well defined, so that the modules themselves
	can be as independent as possible.
      </para>
      <para>
	The most important database fields concerning a job are formatted in
	XML, and conform precisely to specifications that SPK has developed 
	and which are  part of the open source release.  This is an example of the
	leverage obtained from the use of widely accepted techniques and
	standards.  Because SPK employs XML, it was not necessary to 
	develop a special-purpose parser.  Instead, the widely used
	Xerces parser is employed.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title id="lifecycle">The Lifecycle of a Job</title>
      <para>
	Another pillar of the architecture of SPK is the concept of job lifecycle.
	Milestones in the life of a job are implemented as events in a
	finite state automaton, implemented by the three servers and the database.
      </para>
      <para>
	As shown in the following diagram, the web server submits a job that it
	has received from the MDA by adding a new row to the 
	<emphasis>job</emphasis> table of the database and entering the
	value <emphasis>q2c</emphasis> (queued to compile) in the the 
	<emphasis>state_code</emphasis>	field of that row.
      </para>
      <para>
	Meanwhile the <emphasis>compiler daemon</emphasis>, which is a part of the
	application server, will have noticed the appearance of a new job with
	<emphasis>queued to compile</emphasis> status. When sufficient resources
	become available to the application server so that it can compile another
	job, the daemon will start an instance of the SPK compiler to transform
	the job specifications in the database into C++ code. It will change
	the <emphasis>state_code </emphasis> field to <emphasis>cmp</emphasis>
	(compiling).
	If the compilation
	completes without error, the daemon stores the resulting code in the
	job's database row and changes the <emphasis>state_code</emphasis>
	field to <emphasis>q2r</emphasis> (queued to run).
      </para>
      <para>
	As soon as the entry is changed in the database, another daemon which is
	part of the computational server will notice it. In due time, when resources
	become available and when the job is the highest priority job waiting with
	<emphasis>queued to run</emphasis> status, the <emphasis>runtime daemon</emphasis>
	will change the <emphasis>state_code</emphasis> field to 
	<emphasis>run</emphasis>, 
	will have the C++ code compiled and linked to form an executable binary and
	will start it running on the computational cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
	When the job's run is complete, the runtime daemon will store the results
	into the database and will change the <emphasis>state_code</emphasis> field
	to <emphasis>end</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
	The next time the user checks the status of his jobs, either on his personal
	SPK web page or with the MDA, he will notice that a job has results available.
	He will use the MDA to transfer a copy of the results to his workstation
	for analysis, presentation, or export to other tools.
      </para>
      <para>
	<figure float="1">
	  <title>Job State Diagram</title>
	  <graphic scale="45" fileref="job_state.png"/>
	</figure>
	
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Design of the Database</title>
      <para>
	SPK employs the MySQL relational database management system to provide
	the database which is central to its architecture. MySQL is very widely
	used on the world wide web.  It bears an open source license when
	distributed as part of a system such as SPK which is also distributed as
	open source.  Recent versions of MySQL support atomic transactions,
	which is required by the <link linkend="lifecycle">lifecycle</link>
	automaton because changes in job state require simultaneous 
	changes to multiple tables.
      </para>
      <para>
	As explained <link linkend="central">above</link>, the database is
	the central communications path between servers. From the 
	<link linkend="mda">user perspective</link>, it provides persistent
	storage for models and data, as well as a complete history of his
	jobs.  From the point of view of the 
	<link linkend="ssp">service provider</link>, the database maintains
	a history of services and the users to whom they were provided.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the diagram that follows, the rectangles represent the most important
	tables in the database, while the lines that connect them represent
	relationships.  The arrow head at one end of a connecting line
	indicates the direction of the relationship.  For instance, the
	fact that the arrow head on the line between job and user points
	toward user implies that the user <emphasis>has</emphasis> a 
	job, rather than the other way around.  The crow's foot symbol at 
	the other end of the line indicates that a user may have zero or
	more jobs.  If a line has no crow's foot, a row of the table at the
	head of the arrow <emphasis>has</emphasis> exactly one row of the
	table at the foot of the arrow.
      </para>
      <para>
	<figure float="1">
	  <title>Database Diagram</title>
	  <graphic scale="40" fileref="erModelDiagram.png"/>
	</figure>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Application Server</title>
      <para>
	The Application Server for Population Kinetics (ASPK) is one of the three
	logical servers that comprise the server side of SPK. Its main components
	are the SPK compiler and the compiler daemon.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>SPK Compiler</title>
	<para>
	  If it were not for the SPK compiler, users would have to express their
	  models as C++ programs.  The compiler frees them from this very 
	  time consuming and error-prone activity by automatically generating
	  the C++ program from specifications they input into the MDA.  The
	  resulting program can subsequently be compiled by the GNU GCC
	  compiler and linked to several 
	  <link linkend="libraries">libraries</link> to create a highly efficient
	  binary program for run on the computational engine. 
	</para>
	<para>
	  Users can include Fortran-77 statements in their model specifications.
	  The portion of the SPK compiler that translates Fortran into
	  C++ was, itself, automatically generated by the GNU versions of 
	  two classic compiler building tools: the
	  <emphasis>Lex</emphasis> lexical analyzer and the 
	  <emphasis>Yacc</emphasis> compiler-compiler.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The SPK compiler does much more than translate Fortran into 
	  C++, however. It creates an entire driver program which incorporates
	  the users initial estimates, runtime parameters, and output
	  specifications.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The compiler is very efficient. On average, it takes only a
	  few seconds to compile a job.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>The Compiler Daemon</title>
	<para>
	  A Daemon is a program which runs continuously to provide
	  round-the-clock services.  The SPK compiler daemon
	  constantly monitors ASPK resources. When sufficient resources
	  become available to compile another job, the daemon scans the
	  database for jobs with <emphasis>queued to compile</emphasis>
	  status, and picks the job with highest priority.  If several
	  jobs were queued with the same priority, it picks the one which
	  has been waiting the longest.  In practice, the compiler queue
	  is rarely congested, because the compiler takes only a few seconds to
	  process a job.
	</para>
	<para>
	  When the daemon selects a job for compilation, it creates a 
	  working directory for the job, copies the
	  <emphasis>xml_source</emphasis> field from the database to a
	  new file called <filename>source.xml</filename> and extracts
	  the latest version of the dataset referenced by the
	  <emphasis>dataset_id</emphasis> field to
	  create a file called <filename>data.xml</filename>.  It
	  then runs the compiler as a child process, passing
	  <filename>source.xml</filename> and 
	  <filename>data.xml</filename> as arguments.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Because the daemon is the parent of the compiler, it is 
	  notified when the compiler 
	  terminates for any reason, whether successfully
	  or unsuccessfully. If the compilation
	  was successful, the daemon creates an archive (using the
	  Unix <command>tar</command> command) of the entire working directory,
	  and stores it in the <emphasis>cpp_source</emphasis> field
	  of the database. It changes the state_code to 
	  <emphasis>q2r</emphasis> (queued to run).
	  If, on the other hand, the compilation terminated with errors,
	  the daemon places an error message, plus any output that the
	  compiler wrote to a file called 
	  <filename>software error</filename>, in the
	  <emphasis>report</emphasis> field of the database and
	  changes the state_code to <emphasis>end</emphasis>.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Computational Server</title>
      <para>
	The Computational Server for Population Kinetics (CSPK)
	is where the really heavy work gets done. This logical
	server creates an efficient binary program by employing the GNU GCC
	compiler to translate the C++ output of the
	SPK compiler into object code and to link it to the GNU libraries, the
	SPK library, ATLAS, and CppAd. It then runs this binary on the 
	the computational engine.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>GNU GCC Compiler and Libraries</title>
	<para>
	  <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/">GNU</ulink> is the organization that invented
	  open source.  The development tools that they distribute are among the very
	  best.  They are available for essentially all Unix and Linux platforms, which
	  means that SPK can run on all such platforms. The wide availability of these
	  tools provides strong encouragement for cooperative development.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title id="libraries">The SPK Library</title>
	<para>
	  The SPK library is the result of years of cooperative development at RFPK
	  between a scientific team, a mathematics team and a software
	  team.  This C++ class library encapsulates most of the logic 
	  required to do the PK calculation.  It was originally released
	  by itself, but was found to be impractical for most scientists
	  to use because of the difficulty of writing the required driver
	  program.  Now the driver is automatically generated by the
	  SPK compiler.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Atlas</title>
	<para>
	  The Automatically Tuned Linear Algebra Software 
	  <ulink url="http://math-atlas.sourceforge.net/">(ATLAS)</ulink> package
	  provides a C language implementation of Basic Linear Algebra Subprograms
	  (BLAS), and a small subset of a C implementation of Linear Algebra
	  Package (LAPACK), along with an installation program that automatically tunes
	  the software for the particular processor that it will be running on. This
	  software is open source.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>CppAd</title>
	<para>
	  <ulink url="http://www.seanet.com/~bradbell/home.htm">Bradley M. Bell</ulink>,
	  member of the RFPK mathematics team, has developed an 
	  automatic differentiation package on his own time. This excellent package
	  is a strong demonstration of the power of open source. CppAd relieves the
	  user from having to provide derivatives of model functions.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>The Runtime Daemon</title>
	<para>
	  The runtime daemon continuously monitors resources available on the 
	  cluster and compares them with needs of jobs waiting in the run queue.
	  When sufficient resources become available, and balancing the need
	  to efficiently allocate cluster resources with the priority at 
	  which jobs were queued and how long they have been waiting, the
	  daemon selects a job to run and changes the
	  <emphasis>state_code</emphasis> field to <emphasis>run</emphasis>
	  (running).
	</para>
	<para>
	  From the <emphasis>cpp_source</emphasis> field in the database, the 
	  daemon recreates on the cluster the job's working directory, as it
	  was at the end of processing by the ASPK.  It then calls upon the
	  GNU <command>make</command> command to compile the ASPK-generated
	  driver and link it to GNU libraries, the SPK library, ATLAS, 
	  and CppAd, to create a binary tuned to the processors of the
	  cluster. The daemon then starts the binary running on the 
	  cluster as a child process.
	</para>
	<para>
	  When either the <emphasis>make</emphasis> process or the
	  <emphasis>run</emphasis> process terminates, the daemon is
	  immediately notified because it is the parent of these processes.  It
	  creates a file called <filename>report.xml</filename> from
	  the output, then writes the contents of the file to the
	  <emphasis>report</emphasis> field in the database. It
	  changes the <emphasis>state_code</emphasis> field to
	  <emphasis>end</emphasis>.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Web Server</title>
      <para>
	The web server provides the interface between the 
	user with her browser and MDA, and the rest of SPK.
      </para>
      <sect3>
	<title>Java-Based Dynamic Content</title>
	<para>
	  The SPK web server provides both static and dynamic content.
	  Static content consists of web pages which do not change in
	  response to what the user or her jobs are doing. Dynamic
	  content is created on the fly, depending on the state of
	  the system and the course of the interaction with the user.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Static content is created by the service provider.  As a 
	  service provider, RFPK presents information about the
	  organization, its directions, and its products. 
	  Other service providers present similar sorts of information.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The dynamic content is part of the SPK software
	  In particular, the web server acts as a server-side proxy for
	  the MDA when it accesses the database.  Dynamic content
	  takes the form of Java servlets and Java Server Pages (JSP).
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Web Security</title>
	<para>
	  The web server always uses the <emphasis>https</emphasis>
	  protocol, which is also known as SSL, the secure socket
	  layer.  All transmissions between the user's workstation
	  and the server are encrypted.
	</para>
	<para>
	  In addition to encryption, the web server employs certificate
	  based public key 
	  server authentication. This allows a user to log into
	  an SPK service with confidence, knowing that the system
	  he is connecting to is not an impostor.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Java WebStart</title>
	<para>
	  Unlike browser applications such as Java applets or JavaScript, 
	  the MDA is a full computer program.  This allows it to be both
	  more responsive and more reliable than applets and JavaScript are capable of
	  being.  At the same time, it is very easily downloaded
	  via Java WebStart from the
	  SPK web site the first time a user accesses the system, and it
	  is automatically updated from that point onward. The downloading
	  and updating are encrypted by SSL for security. Java WebStart
	  also protects the web site from MDA programs that may have
	  been maliciously modified, because it will refuse to run 
	  any MDA modified in the field.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
	<title>Tomcat</title>
	<para>
	  SPK uses the open source Apache Tomcat web server platform. Tomcat 
	  supports static content, Java servlets, JSP, SSL and Java 
	  WebStart.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>The Model Design Agent (MDA)</title>
      <para>
	The MDA is a complete editor for models, datasets and jobs.  It
	submits jobs and presents results.  In many ways, it is quite
	similar to a class of modern software development tools known 
	generically as interactive development environments (IDEs).
	This is no accident. The MDA is built from an open source 
	Java IDE called NetBeans.  The MDA is, in effect, an 
	IDE for developing programs which embody PK models.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the interest of security and simplicity of configuration,
	the MDA does not access the database directly.  Instead, it
	accesses the database via Java servlets resident in the web
	server. The user does not have to install any MySQL software
	on his workstation.
      </para>
      <para>
	The Internet connection between the MDA and the web server
	is via the usual IP ports assigned for web browsing; 
	namely ports 80 and 443.  This means that users who work
	from behind firewalls will usually not have to make 
	special arrangements with their system administrators in
	order to access SPK.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Hardware Architecture</title>
    <para>
      The diagram below depicts the hardware architecture of the
      SPK service provided by RFPK, except that at RFPK the 
      database server and ASPK server are the same machine.
    </para>
    <para>
      <figure float="1">
	<title>Hardware Architecture</title>
	<graphic scale="65" fileref="physical.png"/>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
      The diagram shows a triple interface firewall.  Such
      a firewall or something equivalent is highly recommended.
      In fact, the security of SPK depends on it.  The firewall
      and network topology illustrated accomplishes the following:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shields the servers on the LAN from all TCP/IP requests
	    originating on the Internet.  Servers on the LAN
	    can, however, send requests to the Internet
	    and receive responses.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shields the servers on the LAN from requests 
	    originating on the DMZ network.  In particular, the
	    LAN is protected even if the web server is compromised.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Passes MySQL database requests from the web server
	     to the database server on IP port 3306.
	    This is the only exception to the previous statement.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Shields the web server on the DMZ network from all Internet
	    requests except http and https requests.  These requests
	    are forwarded by the firewall to the web server and nowhere else.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Uses unroutable IP addresses on both the DMZ network
	    and the LAN.  This increases security by making the
	    servers virtually invisible to the Internet.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The servers on the LAN can freely pass TCP/IP communications
	    between them.  In particular, the ASPK and CSPK have free 
	    access to the database server and, due to the protection afforded
	    by the firewall, can do this without need for encryption
	    or certificated authentication.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>

<!--  LocalWords:  xml DOCTYPE DocBook uw SPK articleinfo revhistory revnumber
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  authorinitials afw revremark RFPK itemizedlist listitem
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  mda Mozilla ssp linkend GCC MySQL CVS RedHat orderedlist SSL
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  Xerces NetBeans IDE WebStart fileref png lifecycle Lifecycle
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  cmp erModelDiagram ASPK cpp CppAd ulink url BLAS LAPACK JSP
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  servlets https JSPs IDEs IP http unroutable CSPK
 -->
