<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
  <!ENTITY cygurl
"http://muir.rfpk.washington.edu:800/HOWTO/CYGWIN-rfpk-HOWTO.html">
  <!ENTITY emacsVersion "emacs-21.2">
]>
<article><title>Emacs Installation HOWTO</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>02/03/2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	Following a brief discussion of the advantages of using
	the Emacs text editor, a process for obtaining and 
	installing the software on RFPK workstations is 
	described.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction: Why Emacs?</title>
    <para>
      Unix
      depends heavily upon text files, both for data and
      for configuration.  This contrasts sharply with Windows and
      various legacy mainframe operating systems, which depend 
      on proprietary binary files, instead.  
      Whereas text editing
      in a Windows environment is usually accomplished using
      the rudimentary Wordpad or Notepad programs, the Unix
      environment offers much more powerful tools.  These tools
      make Unix a preferred environment for text work.  (This also
      applies to Linux, the free Unix-compatible operating system,
      and to Cygwin, a Unix-compatible environment which runs on 
      top of the Windows operating system.)  It should also be
      pointed out that the growing importance of text-based 
      markup languages, including SGML, XML and HTML, is elevating
      the importance of text files in all operating system 
      environments, including Windows.
    </para>
    <para>
      The principal text editors are Vi and Emacs.  
      To underline the importance and the exceptional
      quality of these programs, it is worth noting that they
      were created by some of the worlds most illustrious 
      programmers.  Vi was the work of Bill Joy, the technical
      leader of Sun Microsystems, and one of its founders.  Emacs
      is the work of Richard Stallman, the founder of GNU and the
      open source movement, along with many others, including
      Jim Gosling, the creator of Java.
    </para>
    <para>
      How do you choose one or the other?  This depends on
      the nature of the work that you do.  The two editors
      fill somewhat different roles.  For many years now, Vi has
      been the default editor for Unix and Unix-like systems.
      Whenever you log in to one of these systems, you can be
      nearly certain that Vi will be there.  For this reason,
      at least some familiarity with Vi is a necessity for 
      someone who is doing any system administration or
      application configuration work.  Emacs, on the other
      hand, may be absent on a system that you need to 
      use.  Correcting that problem is the main topic of
      this tutorial.
    </para>
    <para>
      Emacs came originally out of the MIT Artificial Intelligence
      Laboratory.  Though the core of the program
      is written in C, for machine efficiency,
      it is extended in Lisp, for human efficiency.  It is
      this extensibility that sets Emacs apart.  Important 
      extensions, known as modes, add features that understand the
      syntax of the particular file or files being edited.  For
      example, there is a C++ mode that understands the syntax
      of the C++ programming language.  There is an SGML/XML mode
      that understands not only the syntax of SGML or XML in
      general but, if the document starts with a reference to
      a Document Type Definition (DTD), it understands the syntax
      of that particular markup language.  For example, the
      SGML/XML mode enables Emacs to understand the syntax of
      Docbook or the syntax of Xhtml.  Because of the availability
      of many preprogrammed modes, Emacs should be preferred over
      Vi for editing documents which must adhere to complex
      syntax rules.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Which Emacs?</title>
    <para>
      Going back to the 1970s, there have been a number of
      versions of Emacs.  From about 1987 until the late
      1990s, however, GNU Emacs was without a doubt the
      Emacs of choice.  This editor was free, available
      on a wide variety of platforms, and was the product
      of Richard Stallman, the creator of the original
      version of Emacs.
    </para>
    <para>
      Until the late 90s,
      the Emacs user interface was entirely driven by
      commands expressed as keystroke sequences starting
      with control codes.  This design was very efficient
      for experience users, but could be difficult to learn
      and difficult to remember for occasional users.  
      The GNU Emacs developers were on their way to creating
      a menu-driven, more user-friendly version of Emacs, 
      but were proceeding very deliberately.
    </para>
    <para>
      All too, deliberately, in the opinion of some.  A new,
      independent open source project, called XEmacs was
      born with the goal of producing an Emacs with the
      long overdue user-friendly features.  The XEmacs
      project put pressure on GNU Emacs,
      forcing it to catch up with the times.
    </para>
    <para>
      Today we have a choice of two user-friendly versions of
      Emacs.  Although we owe the XEmacs developers a debt
      of gratitude for lighting a fire under the feet of
      their GNU Emacs counterparts, this tutorial recommends
      the use of GNU Emacs for the reasons of guaranteed 
      compatibility and respect for Richard Stallman and
      the GNU tradition.  The
      rest of this document will concentrate on a process for
      obtaining and installing the latest version of
      GNU Emacs.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Installing Emacs in a Linux Environment</title>
    <para>
      Emacs is one of the usual components in a Linux system.
      It is packaged with many optional modes already in place,
      including the PSGML mode and the C programming mode.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install Emacs</title>
      <para>
	If your Linux computer was configured for software development,
	you should already have GNU Emacs installed.  If not, you
	can install the emacs packages from your Linux installation
	cdrom.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install the .emacs File</title>
      <para>
	When emacs starts, it reads a configuration file,
	if one is available.  This file can provide a 
	large amount of customization.  For instance,
	it can provide a list of colors to be used for
	syntax coloring; it can specify a default DTD;
	it can specify many options.  Because it can be very
	complex and usually contains lisp code, a detailed
	description is outside the scope of this 
	document.  Instead, the installation of a pre-made
	configuration file will be described.
      </para>
      <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Open up a shell window in the desktop.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Copy the file
	    <filename moreinfo="none">
	      /opt/download/dot.emacs
	    </filename> from
	    <systemitem moreinfo="none" class="systemname">
	      whitechuck
	    </systemitem>,
	    then concatenate it to the 
	    <filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename>
	    file in your home directory. If there was no
	    <filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename> to
	    start with, this will create one.
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      scp whitechuck:/opt/dot.emacs .
	      cat dot.emacs >> .emacs
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Installing Emacs in a Cygwin Environment</title>
    <para>
      The process that follows assumes that the user had
      already installed Cygwin.  If that is not the case, the
      <ulink url="&cygurl;">Cygwin Installation</ulink> HOWTO
      will help you to accomplish this.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install Emacs</title>
      <para>
	In the following procedure, it is assumed, for sake
	of this example, that the latest version of
	GNU Emacs for Windows is version &emacsVersion;.
      </para>
      <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Decide in which directory you want to install Emacs.
	    This tutorial assumes that you will use the directory
	    <filename moreinfo="none">/usr/local</filename>
	    within your Cygwin environment.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Go to the website 
	    <ulink url="http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/windows/emacs/latest"></ulink>
	    which contains links for downloading the binary distribution 
	    of the latest 
	    version of GNU Emacs for Windows.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    While depressing the <keycap moreinfo="none">Shift</keycap>
	    key, left-click the link to
	    <filename moreinfo="none">
	      &emacsVersion;-fullbin-i386.tar.gz
	    </filename>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A file window will appear.  Select the directory
	    into which you want the file to be downloaded,
	    and click on the <guibutton moreinfo="none">Save</guibutton>
	    button.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    After the download has completed, open a Cygwin shell
	    window and use the <command moreinfo="none">cd</command>
	    command to go to the directory which contains the
	    new file.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <anchor id="fullbin"/>
	    Decompress and expand the file by issuing the command
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      tar xzf &emacsVersion;-fullbin-i386.tar.gz
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Run the Emacs installation program:
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      &emacsVersion;/bin/runemacs
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Add Emacs to your execution path.  In this example
	    we assume that you installed Emacs in the directory
	    <filename moreinfo="none">/usr/local</filename> within
	    your Cygwin environment.  
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Add the following lines to the 
	    <filename moreinfo="none">.bash_profile</filename> 
	    configuration file in your home directory
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      EMACSBIN=/usr/local/&emacsVersion;/bin
	      PATH=$EMACSBIN:$PATH
	    </screen>
	    Test this by first closing all Cygwin shell windows,
	    then opening a shell window and typing
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      emacs &amp;
	    </screen>
	    An emacs window should open up, and run independently
	    of the Cygwin window.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    When you are convinced that everything is working,
	    you can clean up by removing the download file,
	    <filename moreinfo="none">
	      &emacsVersion;-fullbin-i386.tar.gz
	    </filename>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install the PSGML Enhancement</title>
      <para>
	Psgml provides the SGML/XML major mode.
	Once installed, whenever you open a 
	file which has the 
	<filename moreinfo="none">.xml</filename>
	filename suffix, Emacs will be transformed into
	a specialized XML editor. 
      </para>
      <para>
	Emacs will understand the syntax of a 
	<emphasis>well-formed</emphasis> XML
	document.  Essentially this means that 
	elements are delimited by a start-tag
	and an end-tag; that elements cannot
	overlap; and that there is a single
	top-level element, which is the document
	itself.  Emacs will color tags and
	provide automatic indentation in order to
	emphasize this structure and to make it
	obvious if structure rules are
	violated.
      </para>
      <para>
	If in addition to the document being 
	well-formed, the preamble of the document contains
	a reference to a file called a
	<emphasis>Document Type Definition</emphasis>
	(DTD), Emacs will read that file, whether
	it resides on the local machine or somewhere
	on the Internet, and use the information to
	provide additional syntax enforcement as well
	as labor-saving features. 
      </para>
      <para>
	One of the things
	that a DTD (such as the Docbook DTD) does 
	is specify all of the elements that are allowed,
	what tag pairs delimit each element,
	and which elements can be contained in which
	other elements.  Based on the position of the
	cursor within the document, the 
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Markup</guimenu> menu
	provides a list of elements allowed at that
	point.  When you click on one of the elements
	named in the pull-down list, a pair of tags
	is generated automatically.  For speed, you
	can also get tag generation via 
	auto-completion, after typing a key-stroke
	combination and the first few letters of an
	element name.
      </para>
      <para>
	To obtain and install Psgml:
	<orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Go to the
	      <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/psgml/">
		PSGML Project
	      </ulink> page
	      at SourceForge, and follow the link to the
	      download page for the latest release.  There you
	      can download the source file for the latest version,
	      in compressed tar 
	      (<filename moreinfo="none">.tar.gz</filename>) format
	      into a temporary directory.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In a Cygwin shell window, use 
	      <command moreinfo="none">cd</command> to go to the
	      temporary directory.  Use
	      <command moreinfo="none">tar</command>
	      to expand the file.
	      Suppose that the file is named
	      <filename moreinfo="none">
		psgml-1.2.5.tar.gz
	      </filename>; then the command would be
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		tar xzf psgml-1.2.5.tar.gz
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Use the <command moreinfo="none">configure</command>
	      shell script to create a tailored 
	      <filename moreinfo="none">Makefile</filename>:
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		cd psgml-1.2.5
		./configure
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Use <command moreinfo="none">make</command> to 
	      have Emacs byte-compile the lisp programs:
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		make
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Use <command moreinfo="none">make</command> to
	      create the directory
	      <filename moreinfo="none">
		/usr/local/share/emacs/site-lisp
	      </filename>
	      if it does not already exist, and to copy
	      necessary files to it:
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		make install
	      </screen>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install the Cygwin Mount Enhancement</title>
      <para>
	When used in a Cygwin environment, the Windows version
	of GNU Emacs needs a little help in properly handling
	Cygwin pathnames and logical links.
	The enhancement consists of 
	lisp code which you can copy from the RFPK server
	called <emphasis>muir</emphasis>.
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Using two <guiicon moreinfo="none">My Computer</guiicon>
	      windows, copy the file with Windows pathname
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		\\muir\SoftwareEngineers\Download\cygwin-mount.el
	      </screen>
	      to the directory
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		\cygwin\usr\local\share\emacs\site-lisp
	      </screen>
	      on the drive that contains your Cygwin environment.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Byte-compile
	      <filename moreinfo="none">cygwin-mount.el</filename>
	      so that it will execute more efficiently.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Open a Cygwin shell window and input the following:
	      <screen format="linespecific">
		cd /usr/local/share/emacs/site-lisp
		emacs &amp;
	      </screen>
	      This should start an Emacs window.  Move screen focus
	      to that window (normally accomplished by moving the
	      mouse pointer to it) and then perform the following:
	      <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Type ALT-x (hold down the ALT key while
		    pressing the x key).  The cursor should jump
		    to the mini-buffer at the bottom of the 
		    Emacs window.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Type
		    <screen format="linespecific">
		      byte-compile-file
		    </screen>
		    In the minibuffer, Emacs will show the pathname
		    of the current directory, so that you can
		    append to it the name of the file you want
		    compiled.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Type
		    <screen format="linespecific">
		      cygwin-mount.el
		    </screen>
		    followed by the <keycode>Enter</keycode> keystroke
		    and Emacs should compile the file, informing
		    you of success or failure.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Install the .emacs File</title>
      <para>
	When emacs starts, it reads a configuration file,
	if one is available.  This file can provide a 
	large amount of customization.  For instance,
	it can provide a list of colors to be used for
	syntax coloring; it can specify a default DTD;
	it can specify many options.  Because it can be very
	complex and usually contains lisp code, a detailed
	description is outside the scope of this 
	document.  Instead, the installation of a pre-made
	configuration file will be described.
      </para>
      <para>
	By default, the name of the Emacs configuration file is
	<filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename> and it is 
	located in your home directory.  Note that the file is 
	a <emphasis>hidden file</emphasis>
	under Unix, Linux, or Cygwin, because its name starts
	with the dot character.  To see it in the output of the
	<command moreinfo="none">ls</command> command, use the
	<option>-a</option> option.  
      </para>
      <para>
	How does Emacs know where to find your home directory?  If 
	you start it from a Cygwin shell window, Emacs will inherit
	the <varname>HOME</varname> environment variable from 
	the shell.  If you start Emacs from a desktop icon, 
	<varname>HOME</varname> may be undefined.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you ever intend to run Emacs outside of Cygwin, 
	it would be a good idea
	to define <varname>HOME</varname> as a Windows environment
	variable.  You do this in the 
	<guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Environment Variables</guimenuitem>
	screen, reached by the following series of menus:
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Start</guimenu>,
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Settings</guimenu>,
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Control Panel</guimenu>,
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">System</guimenu>,
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Advanced</guimenu>,
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Environment Variables</guimenu>.
	In the 
	<guilabel moreinfo="none">User Variables</guilabel> section
	of the screen, define the variable 
	<varname>HOME</varname>, and specify the full path
	of the directory in which
	your <filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename> file 
	resides (normally the full Windows path of your 
	Cygwin home directory) as its value.
      </para>
      <para>
	To use Emacs for XML, you do not
	have to create or even understand your 
	<filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename> file.  Instead,
	you can make a copy of a file that someone else
	has developed for this purpose.  A suitable file resides on the
	RFPK server named <emphasis>muir</emphasis>.
	The windows pathname of
	the file to copy is 
	<screen format="linespecific">
	  <filename moreinfo="none">
	    \\muir\SoftwareEngineers\Download\dot_emacs
	  </filename>
	</screen>
	You can use the Windows
	<guiicon moreinfo="none">My Computer</guiicon>
	explorer to copy this
	file to your home directory and then change the name
	to <filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename> .
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configure Emacs for C or C++</title>
      <para>
	When Emacs opens a file whose name ends in one of the
	usual C or C++ suffixes (.c, .h, .cpp, .cc, etc.), 
	the CC mode is loaded.  This mode can provide 
	syntax coloring, indentation and parentheses matching,
	as well as interfacing with <command moreinfo="none">make</command>
	and with <command moreinfo="none">gdb</command>, the
	GNU debugger.  The user does not have to do much to
	configure this behavior.  There are some options, however,
	that can be specified in the <guimenu moreinfo="none">Options</guimenu>
	menu. 
      </para>
      <para>
	If you change options, the 
	<guimenu moreinfo="none">Options</guimenu> menu will allow
	you to save them.  The new values are automatically
	appended to your <filename moreinfo="none">.emacs</filename>
	file so that they will be applied the next time you start
	Emacs.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Learning Emacs</title>
    <para>
      Emacs is not too difficult to learn, especially the menu-driven
      version.  There are a number of freely available documents
      that can help you.
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The built-in tutorial is a good place to begin.  Simply
	    start emacs and choose
	    <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Emacs Tutorial</guimenuitem>
	    from the <guimenu moreinfo="none">Help</guimenu> menu.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The GNU Emacs Reference Card.  This is available in 
	    <filename moreinfo="none">.pdf</filename> format on
	    the RFPK server, <emphasis>muir</emphasis>, at
	    pathname
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      <filename moreinfo="none">
		\\muir\SoftwareEngineers\Download\EmacsRefcard.pdf
	      </filename>
	    </screen>
	    Using the Adobe Acrobat Reader, you can print this
	    double-sided, on a single piece of paper, so that it
	    can be folded into a reference card of six panels.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    In the Print window, select 
	    <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">
	      HP LaserJet 5000
	    </guimenuitem>
	    for the <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Name</guimenuitem>
	    field, and  
	    <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">
	      Language Level 2
	    </guimenuitem>	
	    for the <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Print Method</guimenuitem>
	    field.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    In the <guimenu moreinfo="none">Properties</guimenu>
	    menu, select the <guimenu moreinfo="none">Layout</guimenu>
	    page.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    In the <guimenu moreinfo="none">Orientation</guimenu> menu
	    select the <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Landscape</guimenuitem>
	    radio button; and in the 
	    <guimenu moreinfo="none">Print on Both Sides (Duplex)</guimenu>
	    menu select the 
	    <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">
	      Flip on Short Edge
	    </guimenuitem>
	    radio button.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Finally press the <guibutton moreinfo="none">OK</guibutton>
	    button to print your reference card.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The PSGML manual.
	    The Emacs mode for editing XML and SGML is called
	    PSGML.  The principal developer for this module is
	    Lennart Staflin and he has written a manual,
	    called <emphasis>Editing SGML with Emacs and PSGML</emphasis>,
	    which covers the special features that the module has 
	    added to Emacs.  You can get a copy of this manual in
	    postscript from the RFPK server, muir, at the pathname
	    <screen format="linespecific">
	      <filename moreinfo="none">
		\\muir\SoftwareEngineers\Download\psgml.ps
	      </filename>
	    </screen>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The official GNU Emacs manual is available
	    <ulink
	      url="http://www.gnu.org/manual/emacs/">
	      online
	    </ulink>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <para>
      Emacs is the most powerful and most configurable text 
      editor ever created.  We have only skimmed the surface
      when discussing a few of the features of this tool.
      The time and effort needed to acquire, install, and learn to
      use this unique resource will be an excellent investment
      for anyone with a need to edit structured text.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>
