<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
]>
<article><title>SSH CONFIGURATION HOWTO</title>
  <articleinfo>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>April 4, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial version.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>April 18, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Added sections on public key authentication.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
	<date>July 28, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Now using the complete domain name of whitechuck.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
	<date>December 30, 2003</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Revised to be relative to RHEL version 3.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
	<date>March 22, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Returned to use of dsa encryption.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.5</revnumber>
	<date>December 10, 2004</date>
	<authorinitials>afw</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Expanded section on connections originating on a server.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.6</revnumber>
	<date>May 31, 2007</date>
	<authorinitials>ae</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Simplified sending your identity to other server.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	Following a discussion of the importance of 
	<command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
	and the public key authentication 
	method, a process for configuring 
	the capability to establish secure connections between your workstation
	and remote computers without using passwords is described.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction: What is SSH?</title>
    <para>
      Until the mid-1990s, there was no secure way to 
      log into and use a computer from a remote location on the internet.
      The unsecure method that was commonly used was to start a 
      <emphasis>telnet</emphasis> client on the local machine, which
      would then establish a telnet protocol link to the remote
      machine, after which a login program would be run and, if 
      successful, a shell session would be established.
    </para>
    <para>
      The login program required the user to key in a username
      and password.  This type of authentication was acceptable 
      practice during the early days of internetworking, when
      most connections were within college campuses or between
      academic laboratories. There was really very little
      security, however, because neither the authentication 
      information nor message content was encrypted. Anyone
      with the ability to tap a communications circuit could
      eavesdrop or steal a password.
    </para>
    <para>
      An even less secure practice was the use of another internet
      service called <command moreinfo="none">rsh</command>,
      or the remote shell,
      which was very similar to <command moreinfo="none">telnet</command>,
      but which could be set up to establish a connection to a shell
      running on a remote system
      <emphasis>without using a password</emphasis>.
      In this mode, the  application depended completely
      on trust; there was no authentication and no encryption. 
      A companion to <command moreinfo="none">rsh</command> was 
      <command moreinfo="none">rcp</command>, the remote copy command,
      which transferred files
      between systems with a similar lack of security.
    </para>
    <para>
      Well before the internet was opened up to the world in the
      1990s, these practices were obsolete due to their 
      lack of security. With the advent of the World Wide Web there
      was an explosion of the number of machines connected to 
      the internet. There was a need to administer machines
      remotely, but this required secure connections. 
    </para>
    <para>
      A number of projects to develop secure replacements for 
      <command moreinfo="none">rsh</command> and 
      <command moreinfo="none">rcp</command>
      were mounted. The effort that succeeded and was rapidly
      adopted was that of the Finnish developer
      Tatu Yloenen. He named his products 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> and 
      <command moreinfo="none">scp</command>,
      the secure shell and secure copy, respectively.
    </para>
    <para>
      These products were never open source, but they were
      offered free of charge to the Linux and OpenBSD 
      communities for a number of years. Because of the
      importance of this software, this arrangement was not
      satisfactory for the long term. The OpenSSH project
      was launched to create open source replacements for
      the proprietary ones. The OpenSSH versions of 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> and 
      <command moreinfo="none">scp</command>
      have been distributed with OpenBSD and Linux for several
      years now.  
    </para>
    <para>    
      With <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>,
      you can log into a remote machine
      with a high degree of security.  All of the communications between
      your workstation and the remote system are encrypted, including
      a password if it is needed.  It is also possible to establish
      sessions with remote machines without providing a password, 
      in a way that is functionally identical to 
      <command moreinfo="none">rsh</command>,
      except that this can be accomplished
      with nearly complete security.  This mode of operation and the process
      for setting it up will be described in the sections that follow..
    </para>
    <para>
      The <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> command
      can also be used to set up an
      <emphasis>encrypted tunnel</emphasis> between your workstation and
      an application running on a remote machine. This feature is especially
      useful when running an X-Windows application on the remote host.
      The following services are provided:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    All communications are encrypted.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The X-Windows messages, which can be voluminous, can optionally
	    be compressed. This is especially useful over a slow connection.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The user does not have to set up the DISPLAY
	    variable (a requirement
	    for X-Windows). This is done automatically.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Public Key Authentication</title>
    <para>
      When two parties wish to exchange secret messages
      using traditional encryption
      methods (also known as <emphasis>symmetric</emphasis>
      encryption), they must
      first exchange a secret key. Distributing keys reliably has always been
      a problem. With <emphasis>public key </emphasis>encryption, it is not 
      necessary for the parties to share secret keys.  Instead, each party
      has a pair of keys: a private key and a public key.  Each party gives the
      other his public key.  Each party keeps his private key secret, never
      revealing it to anyone else. If a third party discovers one of the public
      keys, it is not a problem.  Public keys can be posted to the world with
      no loss of security.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to send a message, the author uses the recipient's public key
      to encrypt it.  Once encrypted, the only key that can decrypt it is
      the recipient's private key, and only the recipient knows that key.
      This is the method used by
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> for public key
      authentication.
    </para>
    <para>
      When you call upon the <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
      on your machine to connect you
      to another machine, your <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
      sends a connection request
      to the <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
      on the remote machine.  The remote
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
      then generates a random number, encrypts it with
      your <emphasis>public key</emphasis> and sends it back.  Your
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> then decrypts it using
      your <emphasis>private key</emphasis>
      to reveal the original number.  Your 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> sends the
      number back to the remote
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>, proving that you are 
      who you claim to be, since only you possess the necessary key.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Public Key Authentication and the Gnome Desktop</title>
    <para>
      There is a very convenient way that users of the Gnome desktop
      can set up <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> so that they
      can connect to remote machines without having to supply
      a username and password but with a high level of security.
      In order for this to work, <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
      depends on two related applications:
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command> and
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-add</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      When you log into the Gnome desktop, the
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command> authentication 
      agent is started automatically.  It continues to run
      for as long as you are logged into the desktop.  The
      mission of <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>
      is to use your private key to decrypt authentication
      messages sent to your
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> client by the remote
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> daemon.
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>
      is available to provide this service to any 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> started from your 
      desktop.
    </para>
    <para>
      In order to send requests to
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command> and to receive
      responses,
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> must have a communications
      channel. When <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>
      starts up, it creates a <emphasis>unix domain socket</emphasis>
      for this purpose and writes the path-name of the socket to
      standard output. The parent process, which is the Gnome 
      desktop, receives this path-name and uses it as the value of
      the <varname>SSH_AUTH_SOCK</varname> environment variable.
      The Gnome desktop is an ancestor to any process started
      from the desktop, including <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>.
      Processes inherit all of the environment variables of their
      parents, hence <varname>SSH_AUTH_SOCK</varname> is part of the
      environment of every <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> client
      that you run. By querying the value of this variable,
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command> knows which socket
      to use to communicate with 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>
      does not know your pass phrase, hence it cannot decrypt
      your private key.
      This is where 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-add</command> comes in.
      After starting <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>,
      the Gnome desktop runs <command moreinfo="none">ssh-add</command>
      to ask you for your pass phrase, which it then uses 
      to decrypt your private key.  It passes the decrypted private
      key via the Unix domain socket
      to <command moreinfo="none">ssh-agent</command>, which
      caches it for future use.
      It is possible to run 
      <command moreinfo="none">ssh-add</command> several
      times, to add additional private keys to 
      the cache.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="workstation-conf">
    <title>Configuring Password-Free Remote Connection for a Workstation</title>
    <para>
      This section describes the process for setting up the 
      Gnome desktop for password-free connection to remote machines.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Create a Pair of Keys</title>
      <para>
	Open up a shell window. You need to generate your two keys, using
	the <command moreinfo="none">ssh-keygen</command> command:
	<screen format="linespecific">
ssh-keygen -t dsa
	</screen>
	The <emphasis>-t dsa</emphasis> option specifies
	that you prefer to use the dsa encryption algorithm (rsa is the other
	possibility).
      </para>
      <para>
	You will be asked to supply a <emphasis>pass phrase.
	</emphasis> This is 
	very important!  The pass phrase
	is used to encrypt your <emphasis>private key</emphasis> when it is
	stored on the disk of your computer.  If it is not encrypted,
	anyone who
	can break into your computer can steal your private key
	and then enter without challenge any of the machines you have
	set up for password-free connection.
      </para>
      <para>
	Be very careful to select an excellent pass phrase
	It is like the passwords that you use to log in to
	your workstation and other
	machines, but it is even more important because it will provide access
	to multiple machines.  It should have the following properties:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Be at least nine characters long.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Be neither a word nor a given name in any language.</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Contain several digits or special characters</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	Note also that the pass phrase is case sensitive.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you look in your
	<filename moreinfo="none">.ssh</filename> directory
	after running <command moreinfo="none">ssh-keygen</command>,
	you will find that two files have been added:
	<filename moreinfo="none">id_dsa</filename>, which is your 
	<emphasis>encrypted</emphasis> private key 
	and <filename moreinfo="none">id_dsa.pub</filename>,
	which is your public key.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Transfer Your Public Key to the Remote Machine</title>
      <para>
	Next, you need to copy your public key to the remote host
	that you want access
	to. You can use <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>
	to accomplish this.
	In the following
	example, we assume that the remote machine has the domain name
	<emphasis>remote-host</emphasis>.  An IP address or an alias
	could be used instead of the domain name.
	<screen format="linespecific">
cat ~/.ssh/id_dsa.pub | ssh remote-host 'mkdir -p .ssh; cat - >> ~/.ssh/authorized_keys; chmod 644 .ssh/authorized_keys'
	</screen>
	You will be asked to supply your username and
	password for the remote host, because
	public key authentication is not yet configured.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configure Gnome</title>
      <para>
	The final step is performed on your workstation. You need to
	configure the Gnome desktop to call
	<command moreinfo="none">ssh-add</command> when X-Windows
	starts up, in order to ask you for your pass phrase.
	Here is the menu sequence:
	<screen format="linespecific">
<guimenu moreinfo="none">Main</guimenu> => <guimenu moreinfo="none">Preferences</guimenu> => <guimenu moreinfo="none">More Preferences</guimenu> => <guimenuitem moreinfo="none">Sessions</guimenuitem> => left-click
	</screen>
	This will open the <interface moreinfo="none">Sessions</interface>
	window.  Press the 
	<guibutton moreinfo="none">Startup Programs</guibutton> button
	followed by
	the <guibutton moreinfo="none">Add</guibutton> button.  Then
	set the following variables:
	<screen format="linespecific">
Startup Command: /usr/bin/ssh-add
Priority: 70
	</screen>
	Close the window by pressing the
	<guibutton moreinfo="none">OK</guibutton> button.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Verify the results</title>
      <para>
	Log out of the Gnome desktop on your workstation, and then
	restart it.  You should be asked for your pass phrase.  If
	not, check to make sure that you did the Gnome configuration'
	correctly.
      </para>
      <para>
	Open up a shell window on your workstation and connect to
	the remote machine with <command moreinfo="none">ssh</command>:
	<screen format="linespecific">
ssh remote-host
	</screen>
	If everything has been correctly configured, the connection
	should go through without you having to supply a pass phrase
	or password.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you are asked for a password, something is wrong.  Here are
	some things that you can check:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Are the permission mode bits on the 
	      <filename moreinfo="none">.ssh</filename> directory in
	      your home directory of your workstation and on the
	      <filename moreinfo="none">.ssh</filename> directory in
	      your home directory on the remote machine set to
	      775?
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      On the remote machine, are the permission modes on the file 
	      <filename moreinfo="none">~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>
	      set to 644?
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Does a copy of the file
	      <filename moreinfo="none">~/.ssh/id_dsa.pub</filename>
	      in your workstation appear at the end of the file
	      <filename moreinfo="none">~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>
	      on the remote machine?
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="server-conf">
    <title>Configuring Password-Free Connections Originating on a Server</title>
    <para>
      The previous section describes setting up the capability to 
      initiate password-free connections from a workstation.  If you 
      connect to a server via ssh and then wish to initiate
      connections from that location to other machines, the workstation configuration
      will not work, because the gnome desktop is not accessible.
      An alternate configuration that uses <emphasis>keychain</emphasis>
      must be used.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Transfer and Install Your Key Pair</title>
      <para>
	Suppose that the remote server is called <emphasis>server</emphasis>.  
	Transfer your key pair to that machine.  As an ordinary user:
	<screen>
cat ~/.ssh/id_dsa.pub | ssh <emphasis>server</emphasis> 'mkdir -p .ssh; cat - >> ~/.ssh/authorized_keys; chmod 644 .ssh/authorized_keys'
	</screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Configure For Password-Free Outgoing Connections</title>
      <para>
	Using the command <command>which keychain</command>, determine
	whether or not the keychain program is already installed on 
	the machine.  If not,
	download the keychain rpm from 
	<ulink url="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/keychain.xml">
	  http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/keychain.xml
	</ulink> and install it.
      </para>
      <para>
	With your favorite text editor, add the following lines to
	the <filename>.bash_profile</filename> file in your 
	home directory on the server.
	<screen>
keychain ~/.ssh/id_dsa
. ~/.keychain/${HOSTNAME}-sh
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Exit your ssh session with <emphasis>server</emphasis>, then 
	log back in.  Now you should be able to connect password-free
	with host on which you have added your public key
	file (<filename>id_dsa.pub</filename> to the
	<filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename> file.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
