<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
     "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY uw "University of Washington">
  <!ENTITY dept "Department of Bioengineering">
  <!ENTITY prod "SPK">
]>
<article><title>Repositioning SPK</title>
 <articleinfo>
  <author><firstname>Alan</firstname><surname>Westhagen</surname></author>
    <affiliation>
      <jobtitle>Software Team Manager</jobtitle>
      <orgname>Resource Facility for Population Kinetics (RFPK)</orgname>
    </affiliation>
  <abstract>
    <title>Abstract</title>
    <para>
	The greatest challenge faced by the &prod; software product is a 
	scarcity of users.  This paper proposes a reorientation which
    	should provide many benefits, including the following goals:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Many new users.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Cooperative development of &prod;, enlisting
	      collaborators, partners and users.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Harnessing of massive amounts of cheap computer
	      resources to optimize population kinetics models.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Ensuring a central role for RFPK in the future
	      of &prod;, as long as RFPK continues to exist.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Ensuring the future of &prod;, even if RFPK
	      ceases to exist due to non-renewal of its
	      public funding.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </abstract>
 </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>The Current Distribution Strategy is Not Working</title>
    <para>
      The initial beta-test version of &prod; was not released to
      end users.  Instead, copies were provided to seven for-profit
      consulting and software firms working in the field of 
      biomedical research.  The rationale for limiting distribution
      to commercial firms was that, as a publicly funded research
      facility, RFPK ought not compete with the private 
      sector.  Instead, RFPK would form partnerships with the
      firms which otherwise might have been competitors and would
      reach the end users through them.
      These firms, which will be referred to as
      <emphasis>partners</emphasis> in the rest of this paper,
      would add value to &prod;,
      in terms of models, user interfaces and consulting.
    </para>
    <para>
      This distribution strategy has not worked well thus far.
      &prod; has been in the hands of the partners for more
      than six months.  In that time, none of the firms has
      made the effort to run the software.  There are a number of 
      possible reasons for this:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Level of effort to create a model.</emphasis>
	    Although several canned models were included in the 
	    release package, to seriously evaluate &prod; in terms of
	    its own needs a partner would need to create one or more
	    models of its own.  This is not a simple process; it 
	    requires considerable effort and ability at programming in the 
	    C++ language.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Uncertainty about the future of &prod;</emphasis>
	    There are fewer than six months remaining on the National
	    Institutes of Health (NIH) grant that funds RFPK.  Even
	    if this grant is extended for an additional five years,
	    as RFPK has requested, the disposition of the
	    software after that time is not clear.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Uncertainty about licensing.</emphasis>  
	    The current license only allows the partner firms to
	    evaluate and test &prod; for a fixed period of time.
	    Before investing any resources, most firms would like
	    to know what the eventual licensing terms will be.
	    In fact, given the uncertain future of RFPK, most firms
	    would like source code, at least in case &prod; were
	    no longer being enhanced and maintained to their 
	    satisfaction.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Inappropriate platform</emphasis>. One
	    partner who has provided feedback indicates that 
	    its clients would be interested in running the software
	    on Linux clusters.  Population models can take many
	    days to run on Windows workstations.  There is a 
	    clear need to provide a more powerful platform.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The net result of the decision to distribute the software 
      exclusively through partners is that &prod; has no users 
      at all, outside of RFPK.  It will not have users until
      the partners invest resources in evaluating and adapting
      the product to their business needs, or until the distribution
      strategy is redefined.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The Free Object Code Alternative</title>
    <para>
      Free distribution of object code has been suggested as an
      alternative distribution strategy.  Free binaries could
      be offered to the partners alone, or to any organization
      requesting them.  In the case of the partners, being freed 
      from any obligation to pay a license fee might be seen
      as favorable to increased sales and profits.  In the 
      case of other researchers, this mode of distribution 
      would put &prod; in their hands more quickly and 
      cheaply than if the software had to first pass through
      the hands of partners.  In any case, it would clear up
      some of the uncertainty about licensing.
     </para>
    <para>
      Although this strategy could provide some benefits, it 
      still would suffer from lack of any guarantee about
      the future enhancement and maintenance of &prod;,
      because the development of the product would remain
      the exclusive domain of RFPK.  
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Source Code Alternatives</title>
    <para>
      The best way to neutralize fears about the ability of
      RFPK to enhance and maintain &prod; in the future would be
      to offer source code.  This way, a partner or an end
      user organization which felt the software was
      not being enhanced or maintained in response
      to its needs could undertake this work itself.
      If care were not taken, however, in specifying 
      the terms under which the source code
      would be licensed, additional problems would be created.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are two principal ways to license source code:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Not open source.</emphasis>
	    With this alternative, there is no requirement
	    for those who make changes to the source code to 
	    make these changes available to others.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Open source.</emphasis>
	    An open source license
	    requires that those who distribute the software
	    to others must provide the source code, including
	    any modifications they have made.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Source Code Distribution Without Open Source License</title>
      <para>
	Source code for software products has been distributed along
	with object code for many years.  For large expensive commercial
	software systems, this is the norm.  Customers require access
	to source as a guarantee that their investment will not be
	lost if, for whatever reason, the vendor can no longer maintain
	and enhance the software to agreed upon standards.  For their
	part, however, vendors are very reluctant to allow anyone
	other than themselves access to the source because they fear
	their intellectual property and their proprietary ideas
	will fall into the hands of competitors.
	The procedure that is often followed in the commercial
	software marketplace is for a copy of the source to be
	placed in <emphasis>escrow</emphasis>
	with a third party, to be released only in case
	the vendor goes out of business or fails to support the
	product as agreed upon.
      </para>
      <para>
	A major disadvantage of licensing &prod; with a source code
	escrow would be that it could provide an incentive 
	for a partner to take the software owner, namely the &uw;,
	to court if the partner were dissatisfied with the 
	performance of RFPK.  This could easily occur, given
	that the aims of RFPK and those of most for-profit firms
	do not coincide.  If the unhappy partner won its case,
	it could wrest control of &prod; from RFPK.
      </para>
      <para>
	Providing source code directly, without escrow, to partners or end
	users would be even more disastrous.  Within a short
	period of time there could be several groups developing
	their own versions of &prod;, all incompatible with
	each other and with the original.  &prod; would give
	birth to several proprietary products, and RFPK's
	software efforts would thus be marginalized.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Source Distribution With Open Source License</title>
      <para>
	An open source license would protect partners, users, and
	RFPK.  Many successful open source projects have 
	amply demonstrated this.  A discussion of some of these
	projects and the many advantages of software development
	under open source will be summarized in the next section.
	For the time being, it should be sufficient
	to point out that the open source development model is
	superior to the one currently being followed by RFPK.
      </para>
      <para>
	The basic principal of open source is very simple.
	<emphasis>If you distribute software that you received
	under an open source license, you must provide
	the recipients of the software with the same
	rights you were accorded.</emphasis>  In other words,
	if you distribute the software, whether in its original
	form or as modified, you must not only pass along to the
	recipient the source code, but also the right to distribute
	it.
      </para>
      <para>
	The open source license would solve two problems immediately:
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Any incentive a partner or any other user
	      might have to &quot;kidnap&quot; &prod; in order
	      to turn it into a proprietary product would vanish.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Doubts about the ability of RFPK to continue the 
	      development and maintenance of &prod; would no
	      longer have critical importance, since any 
	      of the partners or users or any collection of
	      them could take over this responsibility.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>
	Would not &prod; break up into a number of incompatible versions?
	</emphasis>
	No, because any
	group that enhanced &prod; would have a strong incentive
	to submit the changes to RFPK for incorporation in a
	future release, in order to avoid having to maintain
	the software on its own.  RFPK would remain the focus
	of &prod; development.  It would continue its own program
	of enhancement, but added to this would be the integration
	of enhancements by others.  
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>
	  Why would partners have any incentive to make enhancements,
	  if they were required to give away their source code to
	  competitors or potential competitors?
	</emphasis>
	Because the open source license could be written to	
	insure that models and user interfaces were exempted
	from the requirement to distribute source code.  There
	is already a strong precedent for this.  The most famous
	open source license, the
	<emphasis>Gnu General Public License (GPL)</emphasis> which
	covers an enormous body of software including most of Linux,
	is one of the most strict open source licenses, in that it
	requires any derivative work to be distributed as open
	source. The <emphasis>Gnu Library License (LGPL)</emphasis>,
	on the other hand, allows works which are linked to the 
	Gnu function libraries to be distributed as proprietary
	binaries.  RFPK could pattern its license to be similar
	to the LGPL.
      </para>
      <para>
	<emphasis>
	Would not RFPK and the &uw; forego a lot of revenue by
	distributing &prod; for free?
	</emphasis>
	Not necessarily.  Many
	of the largest commercial software enterprises in the
	world, including IBM, Oracle, Sun and Hewlett Packard
	are actively supporting, distributing and building
	products around open source software.  The key for 
	RFPK is to get users; then biomedical consulting
	and software development work will follow.  For instance,
	a partner may require a certain enhancement to &prod;
	in order to satisfy the requirements of its clients, but
	the enhancement might be low on RFPK's priority list.
	The partner could develop the enhancement itself.  It 
	might make more sense, however, for the partner to 
	provide funds so that RFPK could hire additional developers
	to produce the enhancement, while continuing to proceed
	with its original list of priorities.  This sort of 
	thing happens all the time in the open source world.  
	Many millions of dollars of open source development resource are 
	being provide by commercial enterprises.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Benefits of Open Source</title>
    <para>
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Users are absolutely essential to any software development
	    project. Offering &prod; for free via the RFPK
	    web site would give the quest for new users a tremendous
	    boost.  The need for these users to visit the web site
	    often, for updates, news, and technical information 
	    related to &prod; would greatly increase the visibility
	    of RFPK in all its aspects.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Experience with other open source products, including
	    the Linux operating system, the Apache web server, the
	    MySQL and PostgreSQL database systems, and the Sendmail
	    electronic mail system has shown that in spite of the fact
	    that the software is given away free, much revenue can
	    be brought in from related services.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Open source development methods are equal to or
	    superior to traditional commercial development methods,
	    producing results in less time, at lower cost,
	    with higher quality
	    and excellent usability. These methods have several
	    powerful advantages over traditional methods:
	    <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Open source development teams differ radically
		  from their traditional counterparts.  Rather than
		  requiring all team members to work in close
		  proximity to optimize spoken communication and
		  managerial control, open source teams are often
		  constituted of members who live in different
		  cities and continents but
		  communicate via the Internet.
		  Development tools have evolved to support 
		  this new style of distributed collaboration.
		  In the &uw; setting, these new assumptions would
		  coincide with the goals of flexible time and 
		  telecommuting.  In the RFPK context they would open the
		  door to cooperative development between the
		  core team and contributors around the world.
		</para>
		<para>
		  <anchor id="ssfault"/>
		  To gain a bit of perspective on this, consider
		  SourceSafe, one of the 
		  Microsoft development tools currently in use by
		  the RFPK software team.  Four team members are
		  located in the same office, while one member is
		  in another building.  Although the two buildings
		  are connected via the &uw; network, it is a 
		  common occurrence for the in-office developers
		  to be locked out of the development system while
		  their colleague is accessing it.  On a number
		  of occasions, this situation has persisted for
		  hours.  The problem would only be worse if
		  a need arose for one or more team members to 
		  work from home or from other locations.  The
		  basic flaw is that the Microsoft tools were
		  designed to support traditional centralized
		  development teams rather than distributed
		  collaborations.
		</para>
		<para>
		  In passing, it is worthwhile mentioning that open
		  source software development tools are themselves
		  open source software and, as such, are free of
		  charge.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Users are essential to the testing and debugging
		  of software.  At present, RFPK is at an enormous
		  disadvantage, having virtually no users at all.
		  Free distribution of the software over the Internet
		  would give us the best opportunity to rectify this
		  deficiency.  These users would be self-selected
		  and, as such, would have a professional need or
		  interest in the software.  These are the people
		  who would be most likely to use the software
		  and to help shape it to their own needs.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Support of a user base takes resources.  RFPK
		  is small and is not likely to grow without 
		  additional revenue.  Certainly some users
		  (drug companies, for example) will be well-funded
		  and able to pay RFPK or one of the commercial
		  partners for support and consulting.  Others
		  however, will have to be self-supporting.  This
		  will be completely feasible, given that they
		  will have access to the source code and to 
		  shared information on the RFPK web site.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	    </orderedlist>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Linux is the preferred open source development platform.
	    If the decision were made to offer &prod; as an open
	    source product, it would be logical to port the
	    software to Linux.  This move would have 
	    many beneficial side-effects:
	   </para>
	  <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Linux runs very efficiently on ordinary Intel-based
		PC hardware.  It also runs on more powerful 
		processors, including Alpha, UltraSparc,
		PPC and IBM mainframes. In terms of upward
		scalability, Linux far exceeds any Microsoft
		operating system. 
		This is highly relevant to
		&prod;, since some population models will undoubtedly
		require large amounts of processor power. 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Unlike Microsoft operating systems, Linux is hardware
		independent.  It currently is available on more than
		a dozen processor architectures, whereas Microsoft
		only supports the Intel X86 series.  When a new,
		powerful, processor arrives on the scene, Linux 
		is rapidly adapted to it.  Unless the processor 
		fits into Microsoft's business strategy, which is
		essentially the support of office desktops and
		departmental servers, it is unlikely that a 
		version of Windows will be offered.  
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The need for powerful hardware on which to run
		population models goes beyond the choice of processor.
		When asked whether or not it had evaluated &prod;,
		one of the partners replied in the negative but
		did provide some valuable feedback.  The
		partner said its own clients would
		be interested in a Linux version of &prod; because
		then they could run population models on
		Beowulf clusters.
   	      </para>
	      <para>
	 	Beowulf was a project started by NASA in 1994.  The
		idea was to investigate the possibility of building
		super computers from cheap, generic computer components.
		The technology, which became known as 
		<emphasis>commodity off-the-shelf </emphasis> (COTS),
		leverages mass-produced computer hardware, the Linux
		operating system, the Gnu software development tools,
		and various open source drivers and libraries.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		The approach
		has been enormously successful.  By 2002, 49 Beowulf
		clusters were included in the list of the most
		powerful 500 super-computers.  Beowulf clusters 
		are widely used by universities and government
		laboratories.  They have also found a home in
		private industry.  Hollywood uses them extensively
		for digital film production. For instance, the ray tracing 
		algorithms required for creating the digital images
		in the film Titanic were run on a Beowulf cluster
		of Alpha processors.  Conoco uses a large 
		Beowulf cluster 
		to analyze seismic data for oil and gas exploration.
		Locus Discovery, a bio-pharmaceutical firm, uses
		a cluster of 620 nodes, each containing two 
		Intel PIII processors, to help design new drugs.	
	      </para>
	      <para>
		At present, RFPK owns a small Beowulf cluster, but has
		not made much use of it, given that there is currently
		no Linux version of &prod;.  This would change if
		RFPK adopted an open source strategy. The cluster
		would then become an invaluable development resource.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The Process of Transformation</title>
    <para>
      The following are the major tasks that would transform
      &prod; into an open source product.  Many of these
      tasks would be performed in parallel.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Convert software team workstations to Linux</emphasis>
	  and install the full complement of open source development
	  tools and open source office tools.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Accustom the software team to the open source
	  development environment.</emphasis>  This would not be
	  formal training.  Facility with GNU development software
	  and the CVS source control system and the Unix/Linux
	  environment would accrue during the  porting of &prod;
	  to Linux.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Establish a Linux server</emphasis> to provide a
	  repository for &prod; source code and documentation. 
	  This machine would not have to be new or powerful; any surplus
	  Pentium class PC would do.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Transfer &prod; source code to CVS</emphasis>.
	  Every software development project needs a source control
	  system, to enable several programmers to work on the
	  same source files at the same time without wiping out
	  each other's work, and to keep a complete history of
	  all changes.  Currently, RFPK uses the Microsoft
	  SourceSafe source control system.  The inadequacy of
	  SourceSafe when used by developers in separate locations
	  was described,
	  <link linkend="ssfault">above</link>.
	  The open source CVS source control system, on the 
	  other hand, serves geographically distributed development
	  teams very well.  Version 1.0 of &prod; would be
	  entered into CVS which would control the source from
	  that point onward.  No attempt would be made to transfer
	  the history of the development of previous versions from
	  SourceSafe to CVS.  Instead, the history leading
	  up to Version 1.0 would be maintained as long as 
	  necessary under SourceSafe on the current Microsoft
	  server.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  &prod; currently is built around the NAG optimizer, which
	  is proprietary code.  Before &prod; can be distributed
	  as open source software, a new optimizer must be 
	  developed.  This is an opportunity to leverage the
	  considerable expertise of the RFPK Mathematics Team
	  in this area.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Port &prod; to Linux.</emphasis>
	  &prod; is written in C++, which is a language which
	  originated in the Unix environment.  C++ applications
	  interface with the operating system via a library
	  of Unix system calls.  When C++ runs in a non-Unix
	  environment such as Microsoft Windows or NT, a 
	  library is provided which emulates Unix system
	  calls.  In effect, &prod; is already designed
	  to run under Unix.
	</para>
	<para>
	  As an open source rewrite of Unix, Linux
	  conforms to nearly all Unix standards and conventions,
	  &prod; will compile and run under Linux with very
	  little change.  There are a few Microsoft-specific
	  areas in the code, such as file-locking interprocess
	  communication for the parallel implementation, and
	  the Matlab interface, but these are minor and
	  readily identifiable.
	</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Establish an ftp server</emphasis>,
	  or acquire space on an existing one, from which
	  users would download free copies of &prod;,
	  related software, and documentation.  This machine 
	  would not have to be new or powerful; any surplus
	  Pentium class PC would do.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis>Upgrade the RFPK web site</emphasis>
	  with a section dedicated
	  to the dissemination of &prod; software, documentation,
	  and collaborative communications.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Future Directions</title>
    <para>
      The reorientation of the RFPK software efforts towards
      open source, Linux and Beowulf will open up some very
      promising directions.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Emphasize Scalability</title>
      <para>
	Population kinetic models can vary enormously in the
	amount of processor resource required to run them.  The low
	end of the scale presents no difficulty.  The problem
	can be run on a PC using convenient but inefficient
	languages such as Matlab, Octave, S and R.  The
	high end presents a major challenge but
	&prod; is already positioned to
	make a major contribution.
      </para>
      <para>
	&prod; can be thought of as an engine for running 
	a bio-kinetic models in order to calculate certain 
	unknown model parameters.  Models are software
	separate from &prod;, although they must be designed
	according to certain specifications in order for
	&prod; to exercise them.
      </para>
      <para>
	&prod; is written in C++, a programming language
	which is capable of providing efficiency in numerical
	calculation that equals or surpasses Fortran, the
	language traditionally favored for this type of
	work.  As time goes by, improvements in the 
	efficiency of &prod; will continue to be an important
	priority for RFPK.
      </para>
      <para>
	Complex models with lots of data require lots of 
	processor resource.  For maximum efficiency, such
	models should be programmed in C++.
	Even so, a model may require weeks
	of continuous running on the fastest of PCs.  It 
	is obvious that such long running times are
	unacceptable to many researchers.
      </para>
      <para>
	Just as with many other intellectual and creative 
	endeavors, the largest cost in kinetic modeling
	is the cost of human talent.  A close second is the
	opportunity cost incurred when research and
	pharmaceutical products are delayed.
	The cost of computer resources is at best of 
	tertiary importance.
      </para>
      <para>
	A highly scalable version of &prod; would adapt
	automatically to the computer resources available,
	whether running on a Linux workstation or on
	Beowulf cluster.  On a cluster, the divisor by which
	the run time of a problem would be shortened
	would approach the number of nodes employed.
	A user organization that required faster 
	turn-around would simply purchase
	additional nodes for its cluster.  At present,
	nodes cost less than $1000 apiece.  The 
	cost effectiveness of this strategy
	will double at least every
	18 months for the next two decades, according to
	Moore's Law.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Emphasize Modeling Languages</title>

      <para>
        If the goal is enhanced productivity for researchers,
	we must support modeling languages which are more
	expressive of mathematical and scientific concepts than is C++.
	Among these languages are the following:
      </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Matlab, a general mathematically oriented
	      language, widely used by scientists, engineers
	      and mathematicians.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Octave, an open source language which shares
	      much of the Matlab syntax.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      S and Splus, widely used for statistical
	      analysis and modeling.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      R, an open source version of S.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      SAAM II, a graphical modeling environment
	      for individual kinetic modeling.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	These languages are nowhere near as efficient of computer
	time as C++, but they are surely more efficient of researcher
	time.  In many cases, adding enough additional nodes to 
	a Beowulf cluster to make up for the lowered computational
	efficiency would be a very sound investment.  
      </para>
      <para>
	&prod; already has a Matlab interface.  A migration to open
	source should make Matlab a viable alternative to C++ on
	Beowulf clusters.  Other languages can be added in response
	to user demand.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Develop an &prod; Server and API</title>
      <para>
 	RFPK should develop software for the efficient and
	convenient management of a Beowulf cluster as an &prod;
	server.  Models would be sent to the server via the
	Internet and queued for execution.  If sufficient 
	nodes were available, the model would run immediately;
	otherwise it would wait its turn for access to nodes.
	Status and results would be available over the Internet. 
      </para>
      <para>
	Access to these services would be via a network-oriented 
	<emphasis>
	  application programming interface
	</emphasis>
	(API).  RFPK would develop utilities to access these
	services via the API from PCs, MACs, Unix/Linux 
	workstations and the world wide web.  Equally important, however,
	would be the availability of this API to partners
	and collaborators for the modeling tools
	they would develop.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para>
      The goals listed in the abstract are all achievable, as well
      as many other side-benefits, if &prod; is repositioned as
      an open source project.  This move should be undertaken
      as soon as &prod; version 1.0 is released, which would
      be the culmination of the long and intense development
      effort under the first NIH grant.  Version 2.0 should
      be open source, Beowulf capable, and domain-specific
      language friendly.
    </para>
  </section>
</article>
